GOOD AFTERNOON WELCOME TO THE MARCH 3RD 2020 SIXTH REGULAR
MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN PRESENTS
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT
MANDEL MEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR PRESENTS SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRILL
PRESENT SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR
WONG WONG PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT THANK
YOU. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA LONEY WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL WHO
ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS
THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW MATERIALS AND WE HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITY AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS, ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
RAMAKRISHNA ALONI COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? >> I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE
FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR
WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD, INDIVISIBLE, WITH
LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD, I'D
LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AS S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS
PARTICULARLY JAMES KAWANA AND SUSE YOU KNOW AS THEY
RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE
TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE. MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? >> YES.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE HERE TODAY IN THE
BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER. AND WHEN YOU'RE NOT ABLE TO BE
HERE, THE PROCEEDING IS AIRING LIVE ON G OF TV'S CHANNEL 26 OR
YOU CAN CATCH THE LIVE STREAM AT W W W DOT S.F. G O VTV DOT
ORG IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT PUBLIC COMMENT AND WRITING YOU
CAN EITHER SEND AN EMAIL TO BOSSIE AT S.F. GOV DOT ORG OR
USE THE POSTAL SERVICE JUST ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON
BE GOODLATTE PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO
CALIFORNIA 94102 IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION
AT A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITY ACT
OR IF YOU NEED TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE PLEASE CALL
THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY
CALLING (415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. >> APPROVAL OF THE JANUARY 27TH
2026 BOARD MEETING MINUTES COULD I HAVE A MOTION TO
APPROVE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN
SECONDED BY CHERYL. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
I. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I THERE ARE 11 EYES.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER
PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO THE
CONSENT AGENDA PLEASE CALL ITEMS ONE THROUGH FOUR TOGETHER
ITEMS ONE THROUGH FOUR ARE ON CONSENT.
>> THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE ROUTINE IF A MEMBER
OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY.
I DON'T SEE ANYONE SEVERING ANY ITEMS SO MADAM CLERK PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH FOUR SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN MANDEL
MAN I SUPERVISOR AMILCAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER
ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY
PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER FIVE ITEM FIVE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE 4
MILLION FROM THE GENERAL CITY RESERVE TO THE DEPARTMENT OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT FOR EXPANDED STREET CONDITION
STAFFING AND 150,000 FROM THE GENERAL CITY RESERVE TO THE
HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION FOR COMMUNITY INITIATIVES IN FISCAL
YEAR 2025 THROUGH 2026. >> AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
SIX AND SEVEN TOGETHER ITEMS SIX AND 7 OR 2 RESOLUTIONS THAT
APPROVE MANAGEMENT AGREEMENT AMENDMENTS FOR PARKING GARAGES
THROUGH THE MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY.
ITEM SIX APPROVES THE THIRD CONTRACT AMENDMENT WITH AIMCO
AIMCO PARKING LLC AND THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR THE MANAGEMENT
OF TWO OFF STREET PARKING FACILITIES UNDER THE
JURISDICTION OF THE PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO LOCATED AT PIER 32
AND PIER 74 AN INCREASED AMOUNT OF 12 MILLION FOR A TOTAL
CONTRACT AMOUNT OF 219 MILLION .
>> ITEM SEVEN THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE SECOND CONTRACT
AMENDMENT WITH LAZY PARKING CALIFORNIA LLC AND THE CITY
AND COUNTY FOR THE MANAGEMENT OF TWO OFF STREET PARKING
FACILITIES UNDER THE JURISDICTION OF THE PORT OF SAN
FRANCISCO LOCATED AT TRIANGLE LOT AND SEAWALL 321 FOR AN
INCREASED AMOUNT OF 9 MILLION AND A TOTAL CONTRACT AMOUNT OF
189 MILLION THE MANAGEMENT AGREEMENT AMENDMENTS CONTAINED
IN ITEM SIX AND SEVEN BOTH BECOME EFFECTIVE MARCH 1ST 2026
WITH NO CHANGES TO THE TERM OF FEBRUARY 1ST 2023 THROUGH
JANUARY 31ST, 2032 AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER EIGHT. ITEM EIGHT THIS RESOLUTION
APPROVES THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE
CITY AND COUNTY AND YMCA OF SAN FRANCISCO TO PROVIDE MENTAL
HEALTH SERVICES TO CHILDREN AND YOUTH.
TO EXTEND THE TERM BY ONE YEAR FROM JUNE 30TH 2027 FOR A NEW
TERM OF JULY 1ST 2018 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 AND TO INCREASE
THE AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATELY 1.6 MILLION FOR A NEW AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 11.6 MILLION. >> AND WE CAN TAKE THIS SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NINE. ITEM NINE THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO AUTHORIZE THE TREASURE ISLAND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY TO
EXECUTE THE STANDARD AGREEMENTS WITH THE CALIFORNIA AGENCY THE
DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT UNDER
THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND SUSTAINABLE COMMUNITIES
PROGRAM FOR AN APPROXIMATE AWARD OF 45.1 MILLION TO
INCLUDE 30 MILLION DISBURSED BY CD AS A LOAN TO I C 4.3 FAMILY
HOUSING LP FOR 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT AT TREASURE
ISLAND PARCEL I SEE 4.3 AND AN ACCEPT AND EXPAND GRANT AWARD
OF 15.1 MILLION FOR PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION IMPROVEMENTS ON
TREASURE ISLAND TO APPROVE THE STANDARD AGREEMENTS FOR THE
TERM STARTING ON THE EXECUTION DATE THROUGH MARCH 30TH 2046.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
TEN. >> ITEM TEN THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO ALLOW ADDITIONAL USES
AS PRINCIPALLY OR CONDITIONALLY PERMITTED IN HISTORIC BUILDINGS
CITYWIDE AND TO MAKE CONFORMING AMENDMENTS TO PROVISIONS
AFFECTED BY THE FOREGOING ACTION TO INCLUDE ZONING
CONTROL TABLES AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 11 ITEM 11 ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE PROVISIONS RELATED TO THE
SHARED SPACES PROGRAM TO REMOVE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AS A
COORDINATING ENTITY CONDUCTING DESIGN REVIEW TO ELIMINATE
APPLICATION REQUIREMENTS OF DOCUMENTED COMMUNITY OUTREACH
AND NEIGHBOR NOTICE AND TO ELIMINATE PUBLIC ACCESSIBILITY
AND ALTERNATE PUBLIC SEATING REQUIREMENTS TO AMEND THE
PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO ELIMINATE REQUIREMENTS OF PUBLIC NOTICE
OF APPLICATION AND TO AFFIRM THE SECTION DETERMINATION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 12 ITEM 12 THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO REPEAL THE EXISTING SAN FRANCISCO FIRE
CODE IN ITS ENTIRETY AND TO ENACTING NEW SAN FRANCISCO FIRE
CODE TO CONSIST OF THE 2025 CALIFORNIA FIRE CODE
AND PORTIONS OF THE 2024 INTERNATIONAL FIRE CODE
TOGETHER WITH AMENDMENTS SPECIFIC TO SAN FRANCISCO TO
INCLUDE PROVISIONS FOR FEES FOR PERMITS INSPECTIONS AND VARIOUS
CITY SERVICES WITH AN OPERATIVE DATE OF JANUARY FIRST, 2026
AND TO ADOPT THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEMS 13 THROUGH 37 TOGETHER ITEMS 13 THROUGH 37 ARE 25
RESOLUTIONS THAT INITIATE THE LANDMARK DESIGNATION UNDER
ARTICLE TEN OF THE PLANNING CODE FOR THE FOLLOWING
LOCATIONS. ITEM 13 IS FOR THE ALEXANDER
ADAMS HOME AT 1450 MASONIC AVENUE.
ITEM 14 IS THE HINKLE HOUSE AT 740 CASTRO STREET.
ITEM 15 THE BORNHOLM AT 99 TO VISIT BARROW STREET.
ITEM 16 THE BUENA VISTA FARMHOUSE AT 11 PIEDMONT
STREET. >> ITEM 17 IS THE CHARLES CAT'S
HOME AT 1200 DOLORES STREET. ITEM 18 IS THE DUBOSE TRIANGLE
GREEK REVIVAL HOME AT 2173 15TH STREET.
ITEM 19 IS THE ELIOT M WILSON HOME AT 1335 GUERRERO STREET.
>> ITEM 20 IS THE FERNANDO NELSON HOUSE AT 701 CASTRO
STREET. ITEM 21 IS THE ENGINE COMPANY
NUMBER 44 BUILDING LOCATED AT 3816 22ND STREET.
ITEM 22 IS FOR THE FLOYD SPRECKELS MANSION AT 737 BUENA
VISTA AVENUE WEST. ITEM 23 IS FOR THE GOLDEN GATE
LUTHERAN CHURCH LOCATED AT NIGHT AT 3689 19TH STREET.
ITEM 24 IS FOR THE GUERRERO STREET DOUBLE STICK EASTLAKE
HOUSE AT 1415 THROUGH 1417 GUERRERO STREET.
ITEM 25 IS FOR THE HENRY STREET ROWHOUSES AT 191 THROUGH 197
HENRY STREET. ITEM 26 IS FOR THE HOLY
INNOCENTS CHURCH LOCATED AT 455 FAIR OAK STREET.
ITEM 27 IS FOR THE JAMES C HORMEL MANSION LOCATED AT 181
BUENA VISTA AVENUE EAST. ITEM 28 IS FOR THE JOHN C CLARK
HOUSE LOCATED AT 210 DOUGLAS STREET.
ITEM 29 IS FOR THE BUILDINGS LOCATED AT 560 NO EAST STREET
ALSO KNOWN AS THE KIRBY HOUSE AND 552 NO WAY STREET AS THE
PHENIX BREWERY. ITEM 30 IS FOR THE LAYING HOUSE
LOCATED AT 199 CARL STREET. ITEM 31 IS FOR THE MISSION
DOLORES ACADEMY LOCATED AT 3370 1/16 STREET.
ITEM 32 IS FOR THE LEBANON PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH THE NOMI
VALLEY MINISTRY LOCATED AT 1021 SANCHEZ STREET.
ITEM 33 IS FOR THE POOL BILL HOUSE LOCATED AT 192 LAIDLEY
STREET. >> ITEM 30 FOUR IS FOR THE
POWERHOUSE LOCATED AT 1526 MASONIC AVENUE.
ITEM 35 IS FOR THE SECOND CHURCH OF CHRIST SCIENTISTS
LOCATED AT 651 TAYLOR STREET. ITEM 36 IS FOR THE SHAUGHNESSY
HOUSE LOCATED AT 394 FAIR OAK STREET.
AND ITEM 37 IS FOR THE TIETZ BENEKE HOUSE LOCATED AT 657
GENERAL STREET. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 38.
ITEM 38. THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ADD THE
COMMEMORATIVE STREET NAME CARMEN JOHNSON WAY TO THE 1100
BLOCK OF PIER STREET BETWEEN TURKEY AND EDDY STREETS.
IN RECOGNITION OF HER LIFETIME OF SERVICE TO THE FAMILIES OF
THE FILLMORE NEIGHBORHOOD THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 39.
>> ITEM 39 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MAYORAL APPOINTMENT
OF ALLISON WARNER TO THE REDEVELOPMENT SUCCESSOR AGENCY
OVERSIGHT BOARD. TERM ENDING JANUARY 24TH, 2020
EIGHT. >> CHAIR WALTON.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION
TO AMEND THIS ITEM AND TO CORRECT THE TITLE STATING
COMMONLY KNOWN AS THE COMMISSION ON COMMUNITY
INVESTMENT IN INFRASTRUCTURE. STRIKING THAT ON LINES FOUR
AND FIVE. >> IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED
BY FIELDER AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT AMENDMENT WITHOUT
OBJECTION WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE AMENDMENT IS APPROVED.
>> AND THEN ON THE MOTION AS AMENDED LET'S TAKE THAT SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL AND WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION AS AMENDED
IS APPROVED. >> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
ROLL CALL. SUPERVISOR CHEN IS FIRST UP TO
INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUE TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A HEARING REQUEST
TO ADDRESS SAN FRANCISCO'S UNFUNDED AFFORDABLE HOUSING
MANDATE. SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS AND CITY
OFFICIALS HAVE REPEATEDLY INDICATED THAT HOUSING
AFFORDABILITY IT'S ONE OF THE CITY'S TOP CONCERNS DESPITE NEW
NEWS REPORTS AND DATA TRENDS INDICATING THAT LUXURY HOUSING
SURGE AS THE GENERAL RESIDENTIAL REAL ESTATE MARKETS
STAGNATES AND THAT SAN FRANCISCO HAS SURPASSED NEW
YORK AS THE CRISIS IN THE NATION'S.
THE CITY HAS BEEN MOVING FORWARD WITHOUT ANY SENSE OF
URGENCY TO DEVELOP STRATEGIES AND FUNDING SOLUTION TO DELIVER
THE HOUSING AFFORDABILITY THAT SAN FRANCISCANS NEED
AND DESERVE. IN 2023 THE MAYORAL
ADMINISTRATION IMPLEMENTED A SUBSTANTIAL REDUCTION OF
HOUSING CONSTRAINTS. THE SAME YEAR THE INCLUSIONARY
REQUIREMENTS WERE REDUCED IN 2025 THE PERMIT S.F.
INITIATIVES WERE LAUNCHED AND THE FAMILY ZONING
LEGISLATION WHERE IT WAS ADOPTED.
AND IN 2026 THE DOWNTOWN ENHANCEMENT ENHANCED
AND INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING DISTRICT WAS ESTABLISHED PART
OF THIS INITIATIVE TO ADDRESS OVERALL HOUSING STREAMLINING
AND INCENTIVES. HOWEVER, FEW ARE DESIGNED TO
DELIVER TRULY AFFORDABLE HOUSING TO SERVE SAN
FRANCISCANS TODAY. IN FACT, AS REPORTED TODAY
IN THE SAN FRANCISCO STANDARD, A NEW STUDY CONCLUDES THAT IT
COULD TAKE A MINIMUM EIGHT YEARS UP TO 124 YEARS FOR
UNSUBSIDIZED HOUSING PRODUCTION TO STABILIZE RENTS FOR THE
MEDIAN WAGE EARNER IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I SUBMITTED A REQUEST FOR A BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE
ANALYST'S REPORT TO EXAMINE THE IMPACT AND FORECAST CREATE IT
BY THE REMOVAL OF IMPACT FEES AND INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENTS
THAT HAVE BEEN USED TO SUPPORT THE DEVELOPMENT OF AFFORDABLE
HOUSING. THE EFFICACY OF CITY'S RELIANCE
ON ONE TIME FUNDS OR FUNDS TIED TO MARKET CONDITION VERSUS OUT
OF POSSIBLE REVENUE STRATEGIES AND THE ABILITY OF OUR CITIES
STRATEGY TO MEET THE GAPS OF OUR AFFORDABLE HOUSING DELIVERY
SYSTEM TO MEET THE UNIQUE NEEDS OF PARTICULAR VULNERABLE
COMMUNITIES AND NEIGHBORHOODS. >> NOW IT'S TIME TO MOVE
FORWARD AROUND AFFORDABILITY AND REVENUE STRATEGIES.
THE CITY'S INVESTMENT IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING A STORE
WITH THE MAJORITY OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING DOLLARS ALREADY
COMMITTED TO PIPELINE PROJECTS ARE EXHAUSTED WITH NO NEW
FUNDING COMMITMENTS IN THE WARDS.
IN ADDITION, A CUMULATIVE REDUCTION IN INCLUSIONARY
HOUSING REQUIREMENTS AND IMPACT FEEDS HAS FURTHER CURTAILED
EFFORTS TO GENERATE NEW HOUSING AFFORDABLE NEW AFFORDABLE
HOUSING. SIMPLY PUT, REVENUE FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING HAS GONE DRY.
TOLEDO IT'S BEING DONE TO ENSURE THAT LONG TERM PUBLIC
INVESTMENTS THAT SCALE COUNTER CYCLICAL AND NOT ONE TIME
INFUSIONS. IF THE CITY AND COUNTY IS TO
MEET ITS RENEWABLE OBLIGATION TO PRODUCE 46,598 BELOW MARKET
RATE HOUSING BY 2031 AND THE NEEDS OF LOCAL WORKFORCE
AND FROM THE LOWEST INCOME WORKER TO THE MIDDLE INCOME
HOUSEHOLDS WE NEED STRONGER AFFORDABLE HOUSING INVESTMENTS.
AND WE NEED A STRATEGY TO SET ASIDE NEW AFFORDABLE HOUSING
OPPORTUNITIES SITES AND I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH MY
COLLEAGUES TO DEVELOP A SOLUTION TO THIS CRITICAL
CHALLENGES AND ALSO I AM TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO
RECOGNIZE MARCH 2026 AS WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH MARCH AS A
NATIONALLY RECOGNIZED WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH AND IT'S TIME TO
HONOR WOMEN'S CONTRIBUTION, THEIR LEGACY OF STRUGGLE
AND THEIR INCREDIBLE LEADERSHIP THAT HAS PROPEL OUR COUNTRY
FORWARD THROUGHOUT ITS HISTORY AND THE PRESENT.
IT IS DUE TO GENERATIONS OF AGGRESSIVE ADVOCACY THAT OUR
RIGHTS TO DEMOCRATIC PARTICIPATION, REPRODUCTIVE
HEALTH, GENDER FOR ME GENDER AFFIRMING CARE AND SAFE
AND SAFETY FROM GENDER BASED VIOLENCE WERE EARNED.
BUT EVEN OUR MOST HISTORIC WINS ARE NOT GUARANTEED.
IN 2022 WE LOST OUR RIGHT TO SAFE ABORTIONS AND NOW WOMEN
AROUND THE COUNTRY I PUT A SERIOUS MEDICAL AND LEGAL RISKS
FURTHER THROUGHOUT OUR HISTORY .
THIS RIGHTS WERE NEVER EQUALLY IMPLEMENTED FOR ALL WOMEN.
WE'RE WOMEN OF COLOR WORKING WOMEN, IMMIGRANT WOMEN,
TRANSGENDER WOMEN, WOMEN WITH DISABILITIES AND OTHER GROUPS
WERE NEVER SEEN THE FULL WEIGHT OF THIS RACE REALIZED IT IN SAN
FRANCISCO WE ARE AHEAD OF THE COUNTRY BUT STILL BEHIND THE
TIMES THIS RESOLUTION'S INTENT AND INTENDS TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE
STRENGTH AND BRAVERY OF OUR WOMEN WHO HAVE MOVED OUR
COUNTRY AND CITY FOR AND CELEBRATE THE INCREDIBLE
LEADERSHIP OF WOMEN THAT HAS GONE AND UNDERAPPRECIATED BUT
MOST IMPORTANTLY IT REAFFIRMS I'LL COMMIT OUR COMMITMENT TO
DOING THE WORK NOT STOPPING WHEN THINGS BECOME SECONDARY OR
BUDGET FOCUS IS DRY AND OUR COMMITMENT TO GENDER EQUITY
AND OUR POLICIES IS IMPROVING THE LIVES OF WOMEN IN SAN
FRANCISCO I WANT TO THANK EVERYONE FOR THEIR FOR YOUR
EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP AND BUT I ALSO ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK
MY COLLEAGUES SUPERVISOR MAL GA SUPERVISOR CHEN AND SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FOR THEY OUR PARTNERSHIP AND LEADERSHIP AT
THE BOARD OF SAN FRANCISCO. THANK YOU AND THEIR BEST
ESTIMATE THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD COLLEAGUES
TODAY SUPERVISOR CHERYL AND I ARE INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
AFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT TO CIVIL LIBERTIES,
ETHICAL INNOVATION AND DEMOCRATIC ACCOUNTABILITY
IN THE AGE OF ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE OUR CITY HAS
ALWAYS BEEN A LEADER NOT ONLY IN TECHNOLOGICAL INNOVATION BUT
IN INSISTING THAT INNOVATION REFLECTS OUR VALUES AS HOME TO
MANY OF THE WORLD'S MOST INFLUENTIAL A.I. COMPANIES
AND RESEARCH INSTITUTIONS, SAN FRANCISCO SITS AT THE CENTER OF
A TRANSFORMATION THAT WILL SHAPE SOCIETY AND GOVERNANCE
FOR DECADES TO COME. >> A.I. HOLDS EXTRAORDINARY
PROMISE IT CAN ADVANCE HEALTH CARE, IMPROVE PUBLIC SERVICES
AND EXPAND OPPORTUNITY. >> BUT IT ALSO CARRIES SERIOUS
RISKS, PARTICULARLY IN DEPLOYED FOR MASS CIVILIAN MASS
SURVEILLANCE OR THE DEVELOPMENT OF LETHAL AUTONOMOUS WEAPON
SYSTEMS. RECENT PUBLIC REPORTS HAVE
RAISED CONCERN THAT PRIVATE COMPANIES MAY FACE POLITICAL
PRESSURE OR CONTRACTING LEVERAGE TO DEPLOY ADVANCED
TECHNOLOGIES IN WAYS THAT CONFLICT WITH THEIR OWN
PUBLICLY STATED ETHICAL COMMITMENTS AND DEMOCRACY.
ETHICAL JUDGMENT SHOULD NOT BE OVERRIDDEN BY COERCION.
>> THIS RESOLUTION AFFIRMS THAT RESPONSIBLE INNOVATION MUST BE
GUIDED BY TRANSPARENCY, PUBLIC DIALOG AND A RESPECT FOR
FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS. SAN FRANCISCO'S LEADERSHIP
IN TECHNOLOGY MUST GO HAND-IN-HAND WITH LEADERSHIP
AND VALUES. INNOVATION SHOULD SERVE PEOPLE
AND NOT UNDERMINE THEIR RIGHTS. I RESPECTFULLY ASK COLLEAGUES
FOR YOUR SUPPORT. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> I JUST HAVE A MOTION THAT I'M INTRODUCING TO TWO
SCHEDULING COMMITTEE FOR THE WHOLE FOR MARCH 17TH.
WE'D VOTE ON IT NEXT WEEK. I BACK ON FEBRUARY 10TH
INTRODUCED A HEARING REQUEST FOR A HEARING ON THE WORK OF
THE PROP E STREAMLINING TASK FORCE COMMITTEE.
I HAVE RECEIVED FEEDBACK FROM FOLKS THAT THERE WOULD BE
INTEREST IN HAVING THIS HEARD AT THE FULL BOARD TO ALLOW ALL
OF US TO HEAR AND WEIGH IN ON THE POTENTIAL CHARTER AMENDMENT
THAT I HAVE ALSO WORKING ON DRAFTING AND SO WE ARE GOING TO
ASK THAT THE BOARD SCHEDULE THAT FOR THE 17TH AND THE REST
I SUBMIT THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUBMIT THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING HEARING REQUEST TO EXAMINE HOW THIS YEAR'S
PROPOSED BUDGET WILL IMPACT OLDER ADULTS THROUGHOUT SAN
FRANCISCO. >> SENIORS ARE THE CITY'S
FASTEST GROWING POPULATION IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THE CITY'S SENIOR POPULATION AGED 80 OR OLDER IS EXPECTED TO
TRIPLE IN THE NEXT 40 YEARS, MAKING SAN FRANCISCO ONE OF THE
OLDEST CITIES IN CALIFORNIA. AND MY DISTRICT DISTRICT THREE
HAS THE HIGHEST CONCENTRATION OF SENIORS OF ANY DISTRICT.
I BELIEVE THAT ISOLATION IN SENIORS IS A SILENT HEALTH
CRISIS. >> LONELINESS IS AN EPIDEMIC
BUT ONE THAT DOESN'T GET ENOUGH ATTENTION.
THAT'S WHY SOMETHING WE MAY THINK OF AS SMALL A HOT LUNCH
AT A SENIOR CENTER OR ZUMBA CLASS AT A NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER
CAN IN FACT BE A BIG PART OF THE HEALTH AND WELL-BEING OF
OUR SENIOR NEIGHBORS. >> DURING OUR HEARING WE WILL
ASK RELEVANT DEPARTMENTS INCLUDING DOS HCA AND MORTGAGE
CDD AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE TO PRESENT HOW THEY ARE
APPROACHING THIS YEAR'S DIFFICULT BUDGET CHOICES.
>> THIS WILL GIVE US AS DECISION MAKERS AN OPPORTUNITY
TO UNDERSTAND WHAT PROGRAMS ARE PROPOSED TO BE CUT.
AND MOST IMPORTANTLY IT WILL GIVE NONPROFIT AND CBO PARTNERS
AN OPPORTUNITY TO WEIGH IN. I'VE SPOKEN WITH MANY
NONPROFITS WHO CARE FOR OUR COMMUNITIES EACH DAY AND WHO
PRIMARILY SERVE OLDER ADULTS. EVERYONE IS PREPARED TO
CONTINUE TO HAVE TO DO MORE WITH LESS BUT THEY ARE ASKING
FOR TRANSPARENCY AND A CHANCE TO SHOW THEIR CRITICAL ROLE
THAT THEY PLAY IN OUR CITY. >> WE WANT TO KNOW HOW ANY
BUDGET CUTS WILL IMPACT SERVICES THAT MANY OF OUR MOST
VULNERABLE SENIORS RELY ON EVERY DAY.
AND OUR HEARING WILL PROVIDE THIS SPACE IN AN OPPORTUNITY
FOR JUST THAT AND THE REST OF US.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR SUTTER, SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
>> COLLEAGUES, WE JUST VOTED ON THE NEW FIRE CODE WHICH
INCLUDES A FIVE YEAR EXTENSION OF THE SPRINKLER RETROFIT
MANDATE. NOW THIS EXTENSION PROVIDES
IMPORTANT TIME TO ENSURE THAT THE EXEMPTION PROCESS IS CLEAR,
FAIR AND WORKABLE FOR THE RESIDENTS AFFECTED.
WHILE THAT IS A GOOD STEP FORWARD FOR ALMOST ALL
RESIDENTS AFFECTED BY THIS MANDATE, QUESTIONS REMAIN ABOUT
HOW EXEMPTIONS ARE EVALUATED AND WHAT QUALIFIES AS UNDUE
HARDSHIP. THIS EXTENSION GIVES US THE
OPPORTUNITY AND THE RESPONSIBILITY TO PROVIDE
CLARITY AND CERTAINTY IN ORDER TO MAKE FULL AND PRODUCTIVE USE
OF THIS TIME. SUPERVISOR SAUTER AND I ARE
INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO CONVENE A TECHNICAL ADVISORY
COUNCIL. THE COUNCIL WILL INCLUDE
RESIDENTS IMPACTED BY THIS PURCHASE SPRINKLER RETROFIT
MANDATE TECHNICAL EXPERTS REPRESENTATIVES FROM RELEVANT
CITY DEPARTMENTS AND A MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THE PURPOSE OF THE TAC WILL BE TO CLEARLY DEFINE THE EXEMPTION
PROCESS CLARIFYING CURRENTLY VAGUE TERMS IN THE FIRE CODE
SUCH AS QUOTE UNDUE HARDSHIP AND QUOTE ALTERNATIVE METHODS.
THE GOAL IS TO ESTABLISH TRANSPARENT CONSISTENT
STANDARDS SO RESIDENTS CITY DEPARTMENTS AND ALL
STAKEHOLDERS UNDERSTAND EXACTLY WHAT TO EXPECT.
TIME IS OF THE ESSENCE. WE MUST USE THIS EXTENSION
PROACTIVELY TO DELIVER A FAIR, EFFICIENT AND CLEARLY DEFINED
EXEMPTION FRAMEWORK. RESIDENTS DESERVE
STRAIGHTFORWARD ANSWERS AND A PROCESS THEY CAN TRUST.
I WANT TO THANK DEPUTY ATTORNEY SARA FABIAN, DISTRICT THREE
CHIEF OF STAFF TINA BELL MY CHIEF OF STAFF LAUREN CHUNG.
WITHOUT WHOM WE WOULD NOT BE AT THIS POINT AND IMPACTED
RESIDENTS WOULD NOT HAVE A PATH FORWARD TO STAY IN THEIR HOMES.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SHERYL.
MR. PRESIDENT. MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER? >> THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 230 IS
THE RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. IT IS GENERALLY MY PRACTICE TO
PUT MYSELF LAST IN THESE SPECIAL COMMENDATIONS BUT WE
HAVE A VISITING DIGNITARY HERE WITH US TODAY AND SO I'M GOING
TO START TODAY BY PRESENTING A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO LORD
MAYOR FULLER FERGAL DENNEHY WHO SERVES AS THE HEAD OF THE CORK
CITY COUNCIL. IF YOU WANT TO STAND UP
AND COME UP TO THE PODIUM, THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE WITH US.
I'M GOING TO TALK AT YOU FOR A MINUTE AND THEN INVITE YOU TO
SAY A FEW WORDS. >> OUR SISTER CITY RELATIONSHIP
BETWEEN SAN FRANCISCO AND CORK BEGAN IN 1984 AND CONTINUES TO
THIS DAY. THANKS TO THE WORK OF OUR
SISTER CITY COMMITTEE AND I SEE SEAN KEEGAN HERE.
THANK YOU AND TO THE WHOLE COMMITTEE FOR YOUR WORK.
FOR MORE THAN 40 YEARS THESE CLOSE TIES HAVE LED TO HIGH
SCHOOL EXCHANGES, SPORTS EVENTS, BUSINESS CONFERENCES
AND MORE. SAN FRANCISCO AND CORK SHARE
MANY COMMONALITIES NOT LEAST OF WHICH BEING THE GENERATIONS OF
IRISH IMMIGRANTS DATING BACK TO THE GOLD RUSH WHO CONTRIBUTED
SO MUCH TO SAN FRANCISCO'S FOUNDING AND HISTORY.
TECHNOLOGY, MEDICINE AND PHARMACEUTICALS ARE
MAINSTAYS OF COURIC'S ECONOMY AS MUCH AS THEY ARE HERE IN THE
BAY AREA AND ESPECIALLY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
OUR CITIES HAVE BEEN KEY ECONOMIC PARTNERS WITH A REPORT
BY THE BAY AREA COUNCIL ECONOMIC INSTITUTE HIGHLIGHTING
OUR LINKS THROUGH TRADE, INVESTMENT
AND ENTREPRENEURSHIP. TODAY WE'RE GLAD TO REINFORCE
THAT PARTNERSHIP AND EXPRESS OUR GRATITUDE TO THE LORD
MAYOR FOR HIS LEADERSHIP IN FOSTERING THIS CONNECTION.
THE LORD MAYOR IS A NATIVE OF CORK AND HAS BEEN A PASSIONATE
COMMUNITY ACTIVIST FROM A YOUNG AGE INSPIRED BY HIS FAMILY'S
LEGACY OF PUBLIC SERVICE. HIS FATHER JOHN DANAHER SERVED
AS A CITY COUNCILOR ALDERMAN LORD MAYOR OF CORK, A FOUR
TERM. I'M NOT GOING TO GET THIS
RIGHT. I'M GOING TO SAY TD ALSO KNOWN
AS THAT CHOCOLATE DOLLAR. YOU'RE GOING TO SAY IT
CORRECTLY FOR ME. AND WAS A FOUNDING MEMBER OF
TOKA THE SUGAR COMMUNITY ASSOCIATION KHILJI.
THE LORD MAYOR'S LATE MOTHER WAS ALSO A FOUNDING MEMBER OF
THE ASSOCIATION AS WELL AS A FOUNDER OF CHOKER MEALS ON
WHEELS AND SERVED AS A COMMUNITY COUNCIL SECRETARY FOR
13 YEARS. THE LORD MAYOR HIMSELF HAS
SERVED AS THE CHAIRPERSON OF CORK CITY COMMUNITY FORUM, VICE
CHAIRPERSON OF THE CORK CITY PARTNERSHIP.
CHAIRPERSON OF THE LOCAL COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT COMMITTEE
AND DEPUTY LORD MAYOR OF CORK. >> HE IS ESPECIALLY PASSIONATE
ABOUT YOUTH AND COMMUNITIES DEVELOPMENT, CHAMPIONING ACCESS
TO FACILITIES AND INITIATIVES FOR YOUTH TO REALIZE THEIR FULL
POTENTIAL. HE IS ALSO THE SECRETARY
AND FOUNDING MEMBER OF A LOCAL BOXING CLUB AND A LEADER
IN BUSINESS PARTNERSHIP PROGRAMS.
AND BEFORE I INVITE YOU TO SAY A FEW WORDS I SHOULD
ACKNOWLEDGE THAT WE ALSO ARE JOINED BY THE IRISH CONSUL
GENERAL. THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE AS
WELL. AND WITH THAT WE WELCOME YOU,
LORD MAYOR TO OUR CITY AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> MARGOT THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> BOARD PRESIDENT OF
MANAGEMENT AND HONORABLE SUPERVISOR.
AND THANK YOU FOR THAT LOVELY INTRODUCTION.
AS LORD MAYOR OF CORK IT IS MY HEARTFELT HONOR TO SPEAK TO YOU
TODAY IN THE CHAMBER OF THE PEOPLE'S PALACE.
ON BEHALF OF THE CITIZENS OF CORK IRELAND IS ALSO DISTINCT
PERSONAL HONOR FOR ME BECAUSE MY FATHER WHO YOU MENTIONED
JOHN DENNEHY FOR THE SAME CHAIN OF OFFICE THAT I WEAR HERE
TODAY. MY FATHER WAS LORD MAYOR OF
CORK IN 1984 AND ACTUALLY SIGNED THE SISTER TWINNING
AGREEMENT BETWEEN CORK AND SAN FRANCISCO.
WELL, THE THEN DISTINGUISHED MAYOR OF THE CITY, DIANNE
FEINSTEIN. IT IS MY PRIVILEGE STAND BEFORE
YOU HERE TODAY 42 YEARS LATER TO DISCUSS OUR FRIENDSHIP
AND ALSO TO PASS ON DAD'S BEST REGARDS TO ALL OF HIS FRIENDS
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. THIS IS MY FIRST VISIT TO YOUR
STORIED CITY AND IT'S CLEAR TO ME THAT CORK AND SAN FRANCISCO
SHARE A LOT IN COMMON. WE STAND BEFORE SIMILAR
OPPORTUNITIES. WE ALSO FACE SIMILAR CHALLENGES
. AND OUR PARTNERSHIP IS AN
OPPORTUNITY TO WORK TOGETHER TO OUR MUTUAL BENEFIT.
BOTH CITIES ARE WORKING ON THE REVITALIZATION OR DOWNTOWNS ARE
WORKING TO ASSURE THAT SMALL BUSINESS CONTINUES TO THRIVE.
BOTH CITIES ARE SIGNIFICANT HUBS FOR MODERN INDUSTRY
AND THERE IS VERY SIGNIFICANT ECONOMIC COOPERATION BETWEEN
OUR CITIES. >> OUR CITIES ARE ALSO CENTERS
OF LEARNING AND CAN BOAST THRIVING INSTITUTIONS OF
EDUCATIONAL EXCELLENCE. WORKING IN CLOSE PARTNERSHIP
WITH MAYOR LURIE THE IRISH CONSULATE GENERAL, THE SAN
FRANCISCO CAUCUSES, THE CITY AND WITH THE ASCENT OF THIS
DISTINGUISHED ASSEMBLY WE WORKED DURING THIS VISIT TO
DEVELOP TANGIBLE PROGRAMS OF COOPERATION WHICH REFLECT WHAT
WE HOLD IN COMMON AND OF COURSE THE CHALLENGES THAT WE EQUALLY
SHARE. I WOULD LIKE TO BRING THREE
EXAMPLES TO YOUR ATTENTION. FIRSTLY, SMALL BUSINESS IS THE
BEATING HEART OF BOTH OUR CITIES AND WORKING WITH THE
OFFICE OF SMALL BUSINESS WE PROPOSE TO DEVELOP A PROGRAM OF
EXCHANGE WHERE WE CAN SUPPORT MARKET ACCESS FOR SAN
FRANCISCAN BUSINESS INTO THE EUROPEAN MARKET VIA CORK
AND RECIPROCAL ACCESS TO THE AMERICAN MARKET FOR CORK
BUSINESS. WE HAVE ALLOCATED FUNDING FOR
TWO BUSINESSES AND WE LAUNCHED THIS PROGRAM IN THE COMING
WEEKS CORK CITY HALL AND OUR CITY'S INSTITUTIONS STAND READY
TO ASSIST SAN FRANCISCAN SMALL BUSINESS INTERESTS IN EXPLORING
EUROPEAN MARKETS ACCESS. SECONDLY, REFLECTING ON THE
EXISTING EDUCATIONAL TIES BETWEEN OUR CITIES A
PARTNERSHIP AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO
SCHOOL OF MANAGEMENT AND UNIVERSITY COLLEGE CORK
WOULD BE SIGNED IN THE PRESENCE OF MAYOR IN THE PRESENCE OF
MAYOR LURIE AND MYSELF LATER THIS WEEK.
THIS AGREEMENT WILL LEAD TO COLLABORATIVE ACADEMIC PROGRAMS
AND EXCHANGE OF STUDENTS, FACULTY AND START UP FOUNDERS.
>> OF ALL THE ASSETS THAT A CITY MIGHT BRING, ITS PEOPLE
ARE THE GREATEST. AND FINALLY WE WILL CONCLUDE AN
AGREEMENT BETWEEN GOOGLE, BEATTIE HISTORICAL SOCIETY
AND CORK PUBLIC MUSEUM FOR THE GILBERT P PICO RAINBOW FLAG TO
BE EXHIBIT EXHIBITED INTERNATIONALLY FOR THE FIRST
TIME IN CORK. >> WE LOOK FORWARD TO A
COMPREHENSIVE PROGRAM OF COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT AS BEFITS
THIS PIECE OF WORLD HISTORY AND INTERNATIONAL SYMBOL OF
FREEDOM, HOPE AND LOVE. THIS AGREEMENT ALSO REFLECTS
OUR CITY'S MEMBERSHIP OF THE RAINBOW CITIES NETWORK
AND DEEPLY MEANINGFUL GIFT OF RAINBOW FLAG TO CORK FROM SAN
FRANCISCO CITY HALL IN 2014. WE WERE THE FIRST LOCAL
AUTHORITY GOVERNMENT IN IRELAND TO FLY THE RAINBOW FLAG AND I
KNOW THAT PEOPLE FROM ALL OVER CORK AND IRELAND WILL FLOCK TO
CORK FOR THIS INCREDIBLE MAJOR EXHIBITION.
AGAIN, I'D LIKE TO THANK YOU FOR THIS OPPORTUNITY TO SPEAK
TO YOU TODAY. IT'S TRULY BEEN AN HONOR
AND VERY HISTORICAL FOR ME PERSONALLY.
IT'S BEEN A PRIVILEGE. AND WE TAKE THIS OPPORTUNITY
ALSO TO INVITE ALL OF YOU FROM SAN FRANCISCO OR SISTER CITY TO
COME AND VISIT CORK SOMETIME. THERE THERE'S MUCH POSITIVE
WORK THAT WE CAN DO TOGETHER AND YOU CAN BE ASSURED OF A
WARM CARE ME A FIGHTER FROM EVERYBODY INCLUDING THAT OF ME
AND MARK OF CLARE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. AND THIS AND MR. LORD MAYOR,
I'M GOING TO INVITE YOU TO COME INTO THE WELL AND GET A PHOTO
WITH THE GROUP
. >> ALL RIGHT.
ALL RIGHT. >> NEXT UP DISTRICT SEVEN
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
IF THE FOLKS FROM EDGEWOOD COULD PLEASE COME UP.
>> YEAH, HERE YOU GO. SO THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
YEAH. EXCITED COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
JOINING SUPERVISOR ALAN WONG IN COMMENDING EDGEWOOD AS WE
CELEBRATE THEIR 175TH ANNIVERSARY SINCE 1851 AT WHAT
HAS BEEN A PART OF THE FABRIC OF SAN FRANCISCO AND ONE OF THE
MOST IMPORTANT INSTITUTIONS ON THE WEST SIDE.
>> INTERESTINGLY, WE ARE KICKING OFF WOMEN'S HISTORY
MONTH IN MARCH AND IT IS TIMELY THAT WE ALSO RECOGNIZE THAT
EDGEWOOD, FORMERLY THE SAN FRANCISCO PROTESTANT ORPHANAGE
WHEN IT WAS FOUNDED AND ORIGINALLY WAS FOUNDED BY
WOMEN DURING THE CHAOS OF THE GOLD RUSH THERE WAS NO PUBLICLY
FUNDED AGENCY OR INSTITUTIONS TO SUPPORT CHILDREN WHO BECAME
ORPHANED DUE TO THEIR PARENTS DYING FROM THE VOYAGE OUT WEST
OR WHO WERE LEFT WITH A SINGLE PARENT IN THEIR HOUSEHOLD.
>> SO A GROUP OF DEVOTED WOMEN INCLUDING ALYSSA BETH WALLER
WHO WALLER STREET IS NAMED AFTER AND WORK TOGETHER ACROSS
RELIGIOUS GROUPS TO ESTABLISH AN ORPHANAGE AND IT BECAME THE
CITY'S FIRST CHILDREN'S SERVICES AGENCY AND THE FIRST
CHILDREN'S NONPROFIT IN THE WHOLE WESTERN UNITED STATES.
>> SO LONG BEFORE WOMEN HAD THE RIGHT TO VOTE, THESE WOMEN
FOUNDED THIS AMAZING INSTITUTION SHOWING
EXTRAORDINARY CIVIC LEADERSHIP. SO TODAY EDGEWOOD SERVES MORE
THAN 4000 YOUNG PEOPLE YOUNG ADULTS AND CAREGIVER HOURS EACH
YEAR ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO AND SAN MATEO COUNTIES FROM
LAUNCHING THE KINSHIP SUPPORT NETWORK IN 1993 NOW REPLICATED
NATIONWIDE TO PROVIDING CRISIS STABILIZATION RESIDENTIAL CARE
AND COMMUNITY BASED SERVICES. ATWOOD'S IMPACT EXTENDS FAR
BEYOND THE SUNSET REACHES FAMILIES THROUGHOUT THE CITY
AND BEYOND. I HAVE PERSONALLY KNOWN
FAMILIES WHO BENEFITED FROM YOUR SERVICES WHICH ARE LIFE
CHANGING AND TRANSFORMATIVE. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
EVERYTHING THAT YOU DO. AS SAN FRANCISCO HAS EVOLVED,
SO HAS EDGEWOOD. >> OVER THE DECADES THE
ORGANIZATION TRANSITIONED FROM AN ORPHANAGE TO A RESIDENTIAL
TREATMENT PROVIDER AND ULTIMATELY WHAT IT IS TODAY
A COMPREHENSIVE COMMUNITY BASED MODEL OF YOUTH MENTAL HEALTH
CARE. EDGEWOOD CONSISTENTLY RESPONDS
TO THE CHANGING NEEDS OF FAMILIES AND CHILDREN.
>> IT'S WHAT CHAMPIONED APPROACHES THAT HAVE KEPT
CHILDREN CONNECTED TO THEIR FAMILIES AT COMMUNITIES SCHOOLS
WHENEVER POSSIBLE REFLECTING A DEEP COMMITMENT TO BOTH
CONNECTION AND COMPASSION. I AM THE FORMER DIRECTOR OF A
YOUTH SERVICES AT NONPROFIT. I KNOW HOW CRITICAL MENTAL
HEALTH IS ESPECIALLY DURING ADOLESCENCE WHEN YOUNG PEOPLE
ARE CHANGING AND FORGING THEIR IDENTITY.
MOREOVER, I KNOW SO MANY FAMILIES WHO NEED THE SERVICES
AS IN EDGEWOOD IS A LIFELINE AND SO CRITICAL FOR THOSE
FAMILIES AND FOR THE COMMUNITY. ATWOOD'S WORK ALIGNS DIRECTLY
WITH OUR SHARED COMMITMENT TO STRENGTHENING MENTAL HEALTH
SERVICES, STABILIZING FAMILIES, INVESTING IN PREVENTION, EARLY
INTERVENTION. >> LATER IN TODAY'S MEETING
WE'RE GOING TO BE VOTING TO DESIGNATE MARCH 3RD AS EDGEWOOD
DAY. IT ALIGNS WITH THE SAME WEEK AS
AT WORLD TEEN MENTAL HEALTH MENTAL WELLNESS DAY.
IT HONORS 175 YEARS OF EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE.
THE RESOLUTION ALSO RECOGNIZES THAT THOUSANDS OF YOUNG PEOPLE
AND FAMILIES HAVE FOUND A PATH TO HEALING AT EDGEWOOD
AND REAFFIRMS THE CITY'S COMMITMENT TO YOUTH MENTAL
HEALTH, TO WELLNESS AND HOPE FOR GENERATIONS TO COME.
ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I WANT TO SHARE OUR CONGRATULATIONS TO
YOU, TO YOUR STAFF, TO ALL YOUR PARTICIPANTS AND THE FAMILIES
OF THIS REMARKABLE MILESTONE SHOWN.
>> I WANT TO THANK YOUR BOARD MEMBERS, YOUR SUPPORTERS,
ANYONE THAT YOU HAVE TOUCHED IN THIS 175 YEARS THAT YOU'VE
DONE THIS WONDERFUL WORK. AND THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING
THAT YOU CONTINUE TO DO FOR OUR CITY.
AND WITH THAT, IF IT'S OKAY. PRESIDENT MANDELL, I'D LIKE TO
TURN IT OVER TO SUPERVISOR WONG WHO REPRESENTS DISTRICT FOUR
WHERE EDGEWOOD IS LOCATED. >> SUPERVISOR WONG OKAY.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR YOUR PARTNERSHIP
IN RECOGNIZING THIS EXTRAORDINARY MILESTONE TODAY.
WE WANT TO CELEBRATE 125 YEARS OF EDGEWOOD SERVICE TO SAN
FRANCISCO. THAT KIND OF LEGACY DOES NOT
HAPPEN BY ACCIDENT. IT REFLECTS GENERATIONS OF
LEADERSHIP, COMPASSION AND UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO
YOUNG PEOPLE AND FAMILIES. FROM ITS FOUNDING IN 1851 BY A
COURAGEOUS GROUP OF WOMEN TO THE COMPREHENSIVE YOUTH MENTAL
HEALTH SERVICES IT PROVIDES TODAY.
EDGEWOOD HAS CONTINUALLY EVOLVED TO MEET THE NEEDS OF
OUR COMMUNITY IN DISTRICT FOUR. >> WE ARE PROUD TO BE HOME TO
EDGEWOOD CAMPUS BUT ITS IMPACT REACHES FAR BEYOND ANY ONE
NEIGHBORHOOD. FAMILIES ACROSS OUR CITY RELY
ON EDGEWOOD DURING SOME OF THE MOST CHALLENGING MOMENTS
IN THEIR LIVES AT A TIME WHEN YOUTH MENTAL HEALTH NEEDS ARE
GROWING. EDGEWOOD EMPHASIS ON EARLY
INTERVENTION PREVENTION AND WHOLE FAMILY SUPPORT IS
MORE IMPORTANT THAN EVER. THE WORK STRENGTHENS NOT JUST
INDIVIDUAL CHILDREN BUT ENTIRE FAMILIES AND COMMUNITIES.
TODAY WE CELEBRATE THIS REMARKABLE 175 YEAR LEGACY
AND THE THOUSANDS OF YOUNG PEOPLE AND FAMILIES WHOSE LIVES
HAVE BEEN CHANGED BECAUSE EDGEWOOD WAS THERE FOR THEM.
TO THE LEADERSHIP, STAFF, CAREGIVERS AND FAMILIES WHO
MAKE THIS WORK POSSIBLE, THANK YOU.
AND COMING FROM SOMEBODY WAS A POLICY DIRECTOR AT A CHILDREN'S
NONPROFIT MYSELF VETERANS COUNCIL CHAIRMAN CISCO I
RECOGNIZE THE IMPORTANCE OF YOUR WORK.
WITH THAT I'LL TURN IT OVER TO LYNN DORSEY, CEO OF EDGEWOOD TO
SAY A FEW WORDS. LYNN IS A FAMILY THERAPIST
AND NATIONALLY RECOGNIZED LEADER IN CHILDREN'S MENTAL
HEALTH WITH MORE THAN 30 YEARS OF SERVICE IN THE SAN FRANCISCO
BAY AREA. SHE HAS HELPED SHAPE TRAUMA
INFORMED SYSTEMS OF CARE ACROSS OUR CITY AND BEYOND INVESTING
COMPASSIONATE COMMUNITY BASED SUPPORT FOR CHILDREN
AND FAMILIES. THANK YOU LYNN AND YOUR TEAM
FOR BEING HERE TODAY AND CONGRATULATIONS ON 175
YEARS OF EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE TO SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WONG AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND ALL OF YOUR STAFF
FOR YOUR PARTNERSHIP IN MAKING EDGEWOOD DAY A REALITY AND FOR
YOUR STEADFAST WORK ON BEHALF OF CHILDREN, YOUTH AND FAMILIES
ACROSS THE WEST SIDE AND WITHIN THE ENTIRE CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO. AND THANK YOU PRESIDENT
MENDELSOHN AND THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR YOUR
RESOLUTION LEADERSHIP AND PARTNERSHIP IN RECOGNIZING
YOUTH MENTAL HEALTH. MY NAME IS LYNN DOLCE.
I HAVE NOT BEEN LEADING EDGEWOOD FOR 175 YEARS BUT I
HAVE BEEN THERE FOR ALMOST TEN YEARS AND I'M SO PROUD
AND HONORED TO BE HERE TODAY WITH ALL OF YOU.
>> AND AS YOU SAID, SUPERVISOR MELGAR, OVER THE PAST 175
YEARS, EDGEWOOD HAS CERTAINLY EVOLVED WITH SAN FRANCISCO FAR
BEYOND ITS ORIGINS AS AN ORPHANAGE.
OUR MISSION TODAY IS TO PROVIDE THE PEOPLE PLACE AND PATH FOR
EXCEPTIONAL YOUTH MENTAL HEALTH CARE FOR ALL FAMILIES IN SAN
FRANCISCO. EXPERT YOUTH MENTAL HEALTH CARE
HAS NEVER BEEN MORE IN DEMAND. CHILDREN, TEENS AND YOUNG
ADULTS ARE FACING ANXIETY, DEPRESSION AND TRAUMA
AND CRISIS AT LEVELS WE HAVE NEVER SEEN BEFORE IN ALL MY 30
YEARS I HAVE NOT SEEN IT LIKE THIS BEFORE.
IN A RECENT SURVEY 94% OF CALIFORNIA YOUTH EXPERIENCE
MENTAL HEALTH CHALLENGES EACH MONTH.
EDGEWOOD STANDS AT THE FOREFRONT OF THIS YOUTH MENTAL
HEALTH CRISIS AND WE'RE DRIVEN BY URGENCY AND A SENSE OF
PURPOSE. WE OFFER, AS YOU SAID,
COMPREHENSIVE YOUTH MENTAL HEALTH CARE THAT HELPS FAMILIES
NOT ONLY THROUGH TIMES OF ACUTE STRESS AND CRISIS BUT ALSO
AND MORE FREQUENTLY THROUGH TIMES OF VERY TYPICAL AND VERY
PREDICTABLE STRESS. THIS PREVENTS ESCALATION TO OUR
BURDEN SYSTEMS OF CARE. IT PREVENTS ENTRY INTO FOSTER
CARE OR HOMELESSNESS. >> OF NOTE SAN FRANCISCO IN SAN
FRANCISCO ALMOST 45% OF THE UNHOUSED POPULATION REPORT
UNRESOLVED AND UNTREATED PSYCHIATRIC CONDITIONS WHICH
ARE OFTEN THE RESULT OF UNRESOLVED MENTAL HEALTH
ISSUES. >> FAMILY CONFLICT, TRAUMA
SYSTEM INVOLVEMENT AND ECONOMIC STRESS.
AND THIS IS NOT SOMETHING NEW TO ALL OF YOU.
YOU KNOW THIS BUT IT'S WORTH RESTATING.
EDGEWOOD INTERVENE INTERVENES EARLY AND COMPREHENSIVELY TO
STABILIZE FAMILIES, STRENGTHENS PROTECTIVE FACTORS AND KEEPS
PEOPLE YOUNG PEOPLE HOUSED BY ADDRESSING MENTAL HEALTH
AND BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SYSTEMIC CHALLENGES BEFORE CRISIS BECOME
IRREVERSIBLE. EDGEWOOD PREVENTS YOUTH
HOMELESSNESS BEFORE IT EVEN BEGINS.
FOR EXAMPLE, 95% OF CHILDREN AND YOUTH WHO PARTICIPATE
IN THE EDGEWOOD KINSHIP NETWORK REMAIN HOUSED AND DO NOT ENTER
THE FOSTER CARE SYSTEM. >> AND WE KNOW THAT 25% OF
FORMER FOSTER YOUTH UNDER THE AGE OF 25 IN SAN FRANCISCO ARE
UNHOUSED. >> TODAY WE ARE FOCUSED ON
DEEPENING AND EXPANDING EDGEWOOD SERVICES TO SERVE MORE
YOUTH, MORE YOUNG ADULTS AND FAMILIES.
OUR VISION IS THAT EVERY PERSON REGARDLESS OF A ZIP CODE OR
BACKGROUND HAS ACCESS TO EXCELLENT AND TIMELY MENTAL
HEALTH CARE THAT'S ROOTED DEEPLY IN OUR COMMUNITY.
>> TOGETHER WITH OUR COUNTY PARTNERS PARTNERS WITH LIKE ALL
OF YOU WE WILL ENSURE THAT WHEN SAN FRANCISCO YOUTH
AND FAMILIES FACED THEIR MOST CHALLENGING MOMENTS THEY WILL
NOT BE ALONE. EDGEWOOD WILL BE THERE.
THANK YOU TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR RECOGNIZING
EDGEWOOD DAY AND FOR AFFIRMING YOUR COMMITMENT TO OUR SAN
FRANCISCO CHILDREN TEENS AND FAMILIES MENTAL HEALTH SO
THAT REALLY THEY CAN THRIVE. >> WE REALLY APPRECIATE YOUR
SUPPORT. THANK YOU
. >> DISTRICT SIX SUPER VISOR
DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
>> ANDREW FREEMAN COME ON DOWN .
COLLEAGUES I AM TODAY HONORED TO RECOGNIZE ANDREW FREEMAN, A
NATIONALLY RESPECTED HOSPITALITY LEADER AND ONE OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST DEDICATED CULTURAL CHAMPIONS.
MORE THAN 20 YEARS AGO ANDREW FOUNDED A CHEF AND COMPANY
AND CO A SAN FRANCISCO BASED MARKETING AND PUBLIC RELATIONS
AGENCY THAT HAS HELPED TO DEFINE AND ELEVATE OUR CITY'S
RESTAURANT AND HOTEL LANDSCAPE OVER THE PAST TWO DECADES.
>> ANDREW HAS LED MORE THAN 100 RESTAURANT AND HOTEL LAUNCHES
AND HE HAS CONSULTED TO COUNTLESS OTHERS.
HIS EXPERTISE HAS BEEN INSTRUMENTAL IN SHAPING NOT
JUST BRANDS BUT COMMUNITY EXPERIENCES AND I
COINCIDENTALLY HAD THE PLEASURE OF EXPERIENCE ONE EXPERIENCING
ONE FIRSTHAND ON SUNDAY WHEN WE RAN INTO EACH OTHER AT THE
JAMES BEARD FOUNDATION'S TASTE AMERICA EVENT AT THE IKEA SELL
YOU HALL IN MY DISTRICT. AT ANY GIVEN TIME, ANDREW'S
FIRM IS SUPPORTING MORE THAN 40 RESTAURANTS AND HOTELS.
THAT WORK DOESN'T SOLELY SERVE HIS CLIENTS, OF COURSE.
IT ALSO DRIVES TOURISM. IT SUSTAINS ADJACENT BUSINESSES
. IT REINVIGORATE VIGOR, VIGOROUS
NEIGHBORHOOD CORRIDORS AND IT ENSURES THAT SAN FRANCISCO
REMAINS AT THE FOREFRONT OF THE GLOBAL CULINARY CONVERSATION.
BUT ANDREW'S CIVIC CONTRIBUTIONS AND INFLUENCE
EXTEND FAR BEYOND MARKETING ALONE.
HE SERVES ON THE BOARD OF THE GOLDEN GATE RESTAURANT
ASSOCIATION SPROUTS CHEF TRAINING AND THE OAKLAND
RESTAURANT COLLECTIVE CONSISTENTLY ADVOCATING FOR
POLICIES AND PARTNERSHIPS THAT UPLIFT LOCAL BUSINESSES
AND FOSTER COMMUNITY. HIS LEADERSHIP HAS EARNED
NATIONAL RECOGNITION. HE HAS BEEN NAMED ONE OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO BUSINESS TIMES BUSINESS OF PRIDE OUTSTANDING
VOICES AND WAS RECOGNIZED BY THE HOSPITALITY SALES
AND MARKETING ASSOCIATION INTERNATIONAL AS ONE OF THE TOP
25 MOST EXTRAORDINARY MINDS IN SALES AND MARKETING.
>> HE WAS ALSO HONORED AS PR NEWS CEO OF THE YEAR AND LED
AHF AND CO TO INCLUSION ON THE INC 5000 LIST OF ONE OF THE
FASTEST GROWING PRIVATE COMPANIES IN AMERICA.
BUT WHAT TRULY SETS ANDREW APART IS HIS LOVE FOR THIS
CITY. HE GIVES BACK TO IT GENEROUSLY
SUPPORTING ORGANIZATIONS SUCH AS DRESS FOR SUCCESS SAN
FRANCISCO FOODWISE SAN FRANCISCO'S TRAVEL ASSOCIATION
MEALS ON WHEELS SAN FRANCISCO AND THE RICHMOND SUMMIT AIDS
FOUNDATION. TO HIS CORE, ANDREW FREEMAN IS
A TIRELESS ADVOCATE FOR ALL THINGS SAN FRANCISCO, ITS
RESTAURANTS, ITS HOSPITALITY WORKERS, ITS NEIGHBORHOODS
AND ITS SPIRIT. HE UNDERSTANDS THAT HOSPITALITY
IS NOT JUST ABOUT COMMERCE. IT'S ABOUT CONNECTION.
AND WHEN HE'S NOT PROMOTING OUR CITY'S CULINARY BRILLIANCE, YOU
MIGHT FIND HIM AT BARRY'S BOOTCAMP DINING AT ONE OF THE
MANY ESTABLISHMENTS HE SUPPORTS OR AS A FELLOW DOG DADDY MYSELF
I'M A GREAT TO SEE THIS EXPLORING THE NEIGHBORHOODS HE
LOVES WITH HIS DOG DOLLY. ANDREW THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
YOUR LEADERSHIP, FOR YOUR ADVOCACY AND FOR YOUR
UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO THE CITY WE BOTH LOVE.
IT IS MY PRIVILEGE TO COMMEND YOU TODAY FOR YOUR
EXTRAORDINARY CONTRIBUTIONS TO SAN FRANCISCO.
CONGRATULATE BARRON'S BUT BUT WE'VE BEFORE WE INVITE YOU UP
TO SPEAK ANDREW I DO WANT TO INVITE FIRST AS THE LEADING
USOPC WHO REMAINS ONE OF MY FAVORITE LOCAL RESTAURATEURS
DESPITE LEAVING MY DISTRICT TO GROW HER BUSINESS IN SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD'S DISTRICT. TO SHARE A FEW WORDS AS A
LEADER WOULD YOU COME ON UP AND SAY A FEW WORDS FOR ANDREW
? >> HI EVERYONE.
THANK YOU SO MY SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY.
>> MY NAME IS AS ALINA YUSUF. >> I HAVE I AM A SMALL
RESTAURANT AND BUSINESS OWNER HERE IN SOMERS GO AND I AM
DEEPLY HONORED TO STAND HERE TODAY WITNESSING SUCH A
WELL-DESERVED TRIBUTE TO A TRULY REMARKABLE MAN, ANDREW
FREEMAN. >> I OFTEN SAY THAT ANDREW IS
MY GUARDIAN ANGEL THOUGH IT'S TRUE HE IS GUARDIAN ANGEL TO SO
MANY. AS YOU CAN SEE ALL THE LOVE
AND ADMIRATION REFLECT ALL AROUND US EVERY DAY.
>> THE WAY ANDREW MOVES THROUGH LIFE IS EXTRAORDINARY.
>> LED BY HIS INFECTIOUS ENERGY AND VIBRANT SMILE, HE HAS A
RARE GIFT FOR UPLIFTING EVERYONE IN HIS PRESENCE.
ANDREW IS NOT ONLY A CHAMPION IN BUSINESS AND EXCEPTIONAL A
BUSINESS OWNER HIMSELF. >> TO ME HE IS THE CITY OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND NATIONAL TREASURE .
>> ANDREW, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR UNWAVERING DEDICATION
TO SAFEGUARDING OUR CRAFT AND OUR SKILLS.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR UNCONDITIONAL LOVE FOR CREATING
SPACE AND OPPORTUNITY FOR ALL OF US AND FOR YOU.
>> UNYIELDING BELIEF IN OUR POTENTIAL.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR ALL INSPIRING COMMITMENT
AND TENACITY. >> JUST LOVE FOR THE CITY OF
SAN FRANCISCO. I AM TRULY HONORED TO WITNESS
YOUR HUMILITY AND TO EXPERIENCE YOUR WISDOM AND GENEROUS CITY.
>> THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING AND HUGE CONGRATULATIONS MY
DEAR FRIEND. >> THANKS.
>> WELL, DON'T YOU JUST LOVE SAN FRANCISCO?
>> EVERYBODY? >> I'M VOTE FIRST OF ALL, I
THINK I'M VERY RARELY GET NERVOUS THAN I REALLY AM.
>> THE HUMBLED SO HUMBLED AND I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU TO OUR
SUPERVISOR MATT DORSEY. I LIVE IN YOUR DISTRICT TOO.
AND THANK YOU TO ALL THE SUPERVISORS AND I'LL KEEP IT
QUICK BUT I JUST HAVE TO SAY I ARRIVED IN SAN FRANCISCO
IN 1997 FROM NEW YORK CITY AND I WHEN I LITERALLY GOT
FAMILIAR WITH SAN FRANCISCO I THOUGHT IS THAT OPENLY LGBT
GUY? I JUST FOUND NIRVANA.
THIS IS THE CITY, THIS IS MY CITY AND EVERYBODY ELSE IS
WELCOME TO JOIN US HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SO I HAD WORKED FOR TEN YEARS FOR KIMPTON HOTELS
AND RESTAURANTS AND THEN DECIDED TO VENTURE OUT ON MY
OWN AND WE JUST CELEBRATED OUR 20TH ANNIVERSARY OF AF AND CO
AND I HAVE TO SAY I WENT THROUGH THE PANDEMIC WITH ALL
MY BEAUTIFUL BUSINESSES, MY HOTELS, RESTAURANTS
AND EVERYTHING DIDN'T THINK WE WERE GOING TO MAKE IT BUT THE
CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO WAS THERE FOR ME AND I WILL ALWAYS BE
HERE FOR THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I WILL NEVER TAKE FOR GRANTED HOW LUCKY WE ARE TO LIVE
IN THIS CITY OVER THE COURSE OF THE 20 YEARS I'VE BEEN ABLE TO
REALLY WORK WITH THE MOST WONDERFUL RESTAURANTS, HOTELS,
WINERIES AND EVERYTHING IN BETWEEN AND I JUST
CONSTANTLY URGE PEOPLE TO GET OUT AND ENJOY THE CITY
AND SUPPORT THE RESTAURANTS BECAUSE IT'S ONE OF THE HARDEST
BUSINESSES. EVEN BEFORE ALL THE PANDEMIC
HAPPENED IT'S ONE OF THE HARDEST BUSINESSES THAT I WILL
EVER HAVE. I WANT TO SAY A BIG THANK YOU
TO THE WINNER WHO ACTUALLY IS MY GUARDIAN ANGEL AND AND I
ALSO JUST WANT TO ENCOURAGE EVERYBODY TO GET INVOLVED
IN SOMETHING GET INVOLVED ON A CHARITY BOARD, GET INVOLVED
IN A CITY ORGANIZATION. JUST GIVE BACK TO THE CITY THAT
THAT YOU LOVE AS MUCH AS I DO. ON THAT NOTE, I'LL TELL WHEN I
ARRIVED IN 97 I CAME FROM NEW YORK AND I DIDN'T LOVE IT HERE
I WAS LIKE IT'S A LITTLE SLOW. IT'S A LITTLE QUIET.
I'M A LITTLE BORED. WHAT AM I GOING TO DO?
>> SO MY EMPLOYER DECIDED THAT I SHOULD GO TO A THERAPIST
AND WHEN I WENT TO THE THERAPIST THE THERAPIST SAID TO
ME UNTIL YOU SAY YES TO SAN FRANCISCO, SAN FRANCISCO WON'T
SAY YES TO YOU. SO I SAID YES TO SAN FRANCISCO
AND I NEVER LOOKED BACK AND I LOVE IT HERE AND I JUST WANT TO
SAY IF ANYBODY WANTS TO COME OVER WE'RE GOING TO A LOCAL
BUSINESS CALLED CHOW PISCO TO CELEBRATE RIGHT AFTER THIS TO
SAY SO RAISE A GLASS WITH US AND I JUST A HUGE THANKS I'M
HUMBLED AND HONORED TO BE HERE AND THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU SO DISTRICT NINE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MIDDLEMEN.
AND IF I CAN PLEASE HAVE DR. GREGORIA NOVA CAHILL PLEASE
COME TO THE PODIUM. >> I AM THRILLED TODAY TO
COMMEND DR. CAHILL, DEAN OF CITY COLLEGE MISSION CENTER
SCHOOL OF ESL AND TRANSITIONAL STUDIES.
IN HONOR OF INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S DAY AND WOMEN'S HISTORY
MONTH, DR. CAHILL IS A LEADER IN DISTRICT NINE WHO CENTERS
JOY LOVE FOR COMMUNITY AND A COMMITMENT TO ACCESSIBLE
AND QUALITY HIGHER EDUCATION. >> SINCE JOINING CSUF IN 2000
FOR 20 2222 YEARS AGO, SHE HAS SERVED IN MULTIPLE ROLES
INCLUDING ACADEMIC COUNSELOR INSTRUCTOR WEDNESDAY PROGRAM
COORDINATOR, INTERIM DEAN AND NOW AS DEAN OF THE MISSION
CENTER. >> THROUGHOUT HER CAREER SHE
HAS SUPPORTED STUDENTS ACROSS UCSF CENTERS AND HAS BUILT
STRONG LASTING COMMUNITY PARTNERSHIPS THROUGH HER WORK
IN THE MISSION. >> SHE IS BRINGING A FRESH
VISION TO THE MISSION CAMPUS AND TRANSFORMING PROGRAMS WITH
STUDENTS FRONT AND CENTER. >> DR. CAHILL ORIGINALLY FROM A
SMALL VILLAGE IN SOUTH AMERICA, HAD SHARED THAT HER PERSONAL
JOURNEY HAS TAKEN HER ACROSS CONTINENTS WHERE SHE SAW
FIRSTHAND HOW EDUCATION CAN CHANGE LIVES AND HOW WITH
ENCOURAGEMENT AND SUPPORT STUDENTS WILL KEEP MOVING
FORWARD WITH THEIR EDUCATION NO MATTER THE OBSTACLES.
DR. CAHILL EARNED HER B.A. IN MODERN LANGUAGES
AND LINGUISTICS WITH A TSL CERTIFICATE FROM BELOIT COLLEGE
IN WISCONSIN, THEN RECEIVED REMS AND COUNSELING FROM
CALIFORNIA STATE UNIVERSITY EAST BAY AND FINALLY HER
DOCTORATE IN EDUCATION ON LEADERSHIP FOR SOCIAL JUSTICE.
>> IN 2019 HER DOCTORAL RESEARCH FOCUSED ON
INSTITUTIONAL BARRIERS FACED BY LATIN EXCUSE COLLEGE STUDENTS
TRANSFERRING TO FOUR YEAR UNIVERSITIES AS THE FIRST
PERSON IN AN AFRO BOLIVIAN FAMILY TO EARN A DOCTORATE.
DR. CAHILL HAS DEDICATED HER CAREER TO ADVANCING EDUCATIONAL
EQUITY. >> SHE BELIEVES EQUITY CENTERED
LEADERSHIP REQUIRES COURAGE FOSTERING, BELONGING, AFFIRMING
IDENTITIES AND RECOGNIZING THE INHERENT WORTH OF EVERY STUDENT
THROUGH INCLUSIVE PROGRAMS, COLLABORATION AND MENTORSHIP.
SHE WORKS TO ENSURE THAT STUDENTS ACROSS FRANCISCO FEEL
WELCOMED, SUPPORTED AND EMPOWERED TO ACHIEVE
AND EXPAND THEIR EDUCATIONAL GOALS.
>> I THINK IT'S FITTING TO HEAR A FEW QUOTES ABOUT DR. KAEL'S
WORK FROM THOSE DIRECTLY IMPACTED BY HER LEADERSHIP.
>> FORMER CC FUENTES STUDENT ADRIANA HERRERA POSEY STATED
QUOTE DR. CAHILL HAS CREATED INCLUSIVE SPACE AND BY OFFERING
MENTORSHIP AND ADVOCACY. >> HER LEADERSHIP HAS HELPED
FIRST GENERATION STUDENTS OVERCOME SYSTEMIC BARRIERS.
AND FROM AMY MYLES, CURRENT ENGLISH PROFESSOR.
SHARED QUOTE DR. CAHILL LEADS WITH CORAZON RENAUD.
>> SHE WALKS THROUGH MISSION CENTER CARING HER STAND YOUR
NOTEBOOK WRITING DOWN CONCERNS AND IDEAS FROM STUDENTS FACULTY
,STAFF AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND WORKS TIRELESSLY TO MAKE
THE MISSION CENTER A PLACE WHERE PEOPLE FEEL SAFE, SEEN
AND HEARD. >> DR. CAHILL, THANK YOU FOR
YOUR EXEMPLARY LEADERSHIP AT CITY COLLEGE AND FOR MAKING A
DIFFERENCE EVERY DAY FOR STUDENTS IN DISTRICT NINE
AND ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH AND BE FOR
YOU SO MUCH. >> HOLD UP.
HOLD ON. HOLD ON.
SORRY WE HAVE MULTIPLE SUPERVISORS UP HERE WHO LOVE
YOU SO YOU HAVE TO WAIT. THE SUPERVISOR FOR THE OGLALA I
CAN'T LET THE OPPORTUNITY GO BY WITHOUT TELLING YOU HOW
WONDERFUL YOU ARE BECAUSE YOU KNOW I LOVE YOU AND HAVE KNOWN
YOU FOR SOME TIME AND HAVE BEEN JUST YOU KNOW MY BREATH HAS
BEEN TAKEN AWAY BY YOUR ABILITY TO CONNECT PEOPLE TO
OPPORTUNITIES AND YOUR PASSION TO DO THAT.
I'VE WITNESSED IT. >> I'VE SEEN IT IN THE FACE OF
YOUR STUDENTS BUT ALSO YOUR STAFF WHO HAVE SUCH DEEP
RESPECT FOR YOU AND IT IS RARE WHEN YOU KNOW WE SEE AN
EDUCATIONAL LEADER THAT EVERYONE ALWAYS AGREED BECAUSE
YOU KNOW IN YOUR ROLE YOU ALSO HAVE TO TELL PEOPLE WHAT TO DO
AND HOW TO DO IT AND THEN SOMETIMES PEOPLE DISAGREE BUT
EVERYBODY FOLLOWS YOUR VISION AND YOUR DEEP COMMITMENT
AND PASSION TO OPEN DOORS FOR THOSE WHO IN THIS COUNTRY HAVE
COME AND DON'T HAVE, YOU KNOW, A READY PATH AND YOU HAVE
ALWAYS BEEN THAT SORT OF UNWAVERING LEADER TO CONNECT
PEOPLE TO OPPORTUNITY. SO THROUGH ALL THE PROGRAMS
THROUGH THE WAY THAT YOU CONNECT TO COMMUNITY, TO THE
RELATIONSHIPS YOU HAVE IN THE COMMUNITY FROM CITY COLLEGE BUT
ALSO EMPLOYERS AND PEOPLE WHO ARE THERE TO OPEN DOORS FOR
YOUR GRADUATES. SO I THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
EVERYTHING THAT YOU DO FOR THE COMMUNITY AND AS A WOMAN LEADER
I'M SO PROUD THAT WE ARE HONORING YOU TODAY.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR RECOGNIZING THIS AMAZING
WOMAN AND EVERYTHING THAT SHE'S DONE.
AND I WANT TO ALSO THANK YOUR STAFF FOR BEING HERE TO SUPPORT
BECAUSE THAT'S ALSO A TESTAMENT TO HOW MUCH YOU ARE BELOVED
AND HOW WONDERFUL YOU ARE. SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH,
PRESIDENT. >> THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS INCREDIBLE HONOR.
I AM GRATEFUL TO STAND HERE WITH ALL OF YOU LEADERS MENTOR
PEERS, COLLEAGUES, NEIGHBORS, COMMUNITY MEMBERS, FRIENDS
AND FAMILY PEOPLE WHO DO THE DAILY WORK OF LIFTING OTHERS
OPENING DOORS AND STRENGTHENING OUR COMMUNITY.
>> YOUR PRESENCE MEANS SO MUCH TO ME THAT I CANNOT EVEN
EXPRESS. >> I'M ESPECIALLY HUMBLED TO
RECEIVE THIS RECOGNITION DURING WOMEN'S HISTORY MONTH IN A TIME
WHERE WE RECOGNIZE AND HONOR THE LEADERSHIP RESILIENCE
AND CONTRIBUTION OF WOMEN WHO HAVE OPENED THE DOORS FOR
FUTURE GENERATION. >> TODAY I ALSO WANT TO HONOR
THE COUNTLESS WOMEN PAST AND PRESENT WHOSE COURAGE
AND QUIET LEADERSHIP CONTINUED TO SHAPE OUR FAMILY, COMMUNITY
AND SCHOOLS. THERE IS A SAYING THAT WE ALL
KNOW IT TAKES A VILLAGE TO RAISE A CHILD.
THROUGH MY LIFE AND CAREER I'VE ALSO LEARNED THAT IT HELP.
>> IT TAKES A VILLAGE TO HELP INDIVIDUALS GROW LEAD
AND SERVE. >> I WAS FORTUNATE TO GROW INTO
KENYA, BOLIVIA WHERE I EXPERIENCE WHERE THE TRUE
VILLAGE LOOKS LIKE A COMMUNITY GROUNDED IN SHARED
RESPONSIBILITY AND MUTUAL RESPECT.
THE LESSON HAS GUIDED ME AT CITY COLLEGE OF SAN FRANCISCO
MISSION CENTER WHERE WE PREPARE FOR THE WORKFORCE, SUPPORT
FAMILIES AND OPEN OPPORTUNITIES FOR ALL OTHERS.
>> MY VILLAGE HAS GROWN AS YOU CAN NOTICE FROM MENTORS JOYCE
HAYES, ELIZABETH BRANDT, HENRY AUGUSTIN, PHYLLIS KAPLAN,
CARLOTA DEL PORTILLO, GLORIA START HORRIBLE ERIK HERZ
LISETTE ROMANO AND OUR CHANCELLOR OF CITY COLLEGE OF
SAN FRANCISCO KIMBERLY MESSINA AND MANY OTHERS SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. THANK YOU FOR BEING PART OF
THIS WONDERFUL VILLAGE FOR YOUR CONTINUED SUPPORT TO CITY
COLLEGE OF SAN FRANCISCO AND ESPECIALLY YOUR LEADERSHIP
IN SUSTAINING THE FREE CITY PROGRAM WHICH KEEPS EDUCATIONAL
ACCESS ABOVE ALL WITHIN REACH FOR MANY OF OUR FAMILIES.
>> I STAND HERE HUMBLED AND COMMITTED TO LIFT IN OTHERS
BECAUSE I HAVE BEEN LIFTED MANY MANY TIMES FOR MY FROM MY
VILLAGE BECAUSE WHEN WE INVEST IN WOMEN IN THEIR SO ON EACH
OTHER WE STRENGTHEN SAN FRANCISCO FOR A BETTER FUTURE.
THANK YOU SO MUCH
. THIS IS REALLY LET ME JUST
DOUBLE CHECK. YEAH YOU CAN YOU CAN AMEND IT
AND THEN SEND IT TO COMMITTEE AS AMENDED FOR THE FULL YEAH.
SO OH THIS IS ABOUT A PROPONENT VALID ARGUMENT BUT I'M GOING TO
SAY BECAUSE WE HAVE SOME TIME TO OKAY.
YEAH I JUST WANT TO KNOW. YEAH.
>> UH OKAY. NATE BERG WHERE ARE YOU AT?
>> CAN YOU BRING YOUR PEOPLE UP HERE PLEASE?
>> THAT'S IT. SPECIFICALLY I FEEL LIKE THAT
MIGHT BE BEN VAN HOUTEN AND, UH ,MAYBE GREG KERRY AND, UH,
CHRIS CARRINGTON AND GREG SEROTA AND MANNY IS HERE.
ALL RIGHT. I THINK WE GOT OUR CREW.
>> OKAY, GOOD. ALL RIGHT, SO COLLEAGUES, TODAY
I AM EXCITED TO COMMEND THE ORGANIZERS OF THE 2025 CASTRO
HALLOWEEN NIGHT MARKETS. THE CASTRO'S HALLOWEEN
CELEBRATION BEGAN LONG AGO AND FAR AWAY AS A SMALL
CHILDREN'S HALLOWEEN FESTIVAL HOSTED BY CLIFF'S VARIETY STORE
IN 1948. AND YES, THANK YOU.
AND OVER THE DECADES GREW INTO ONE OF THE LARGEST, GAYEST
AND MOST ICONIC HALLOWEEN CELEBRATIONS IN THE WORLD.
>> BY THE 1970S, THIS MAGICAL TRADITION HAD BECOME ONE OF THE
CASTRO'S GREATEST SOURCES OF PRIDE AND JOY.
IN FACT, AS A NEWLY OUT GAY MAN IN THE 90S I HAVE SUPER FOND
MEMORIES OF SOME OF THE ARTISTRY THAT WAS HAPPENING
IN WINDOWS AND AND ALL OF THE AMAZINGNESS OF THAT OF THAT
TIME. BUT BY THE EARLY 2000S THE
CELEBRATION WAS DRAWING HUNDREDS AND THOUSANDS OF PARTY
HUNDREDS AND THOUSANDS, HUNDREDS AND HUNDREDS OF
THOUSANDS OF THOUSANDS OF PARTIERS AND WAS SPIRALING OUT
OF CONTROL, OVERWHELMING STREETS STRETCHING PUBLIC
TRANSIT TO A BREAKING POINT AND CAUSING CHAOS.
A SERIES OF INCREASINGLY VIOLENT CELEBRATIONS INCLUDED A
1924 STABBING THAT INJURED FOUR AND A 29 MASS SHOOTING THAT
INJURED NINE. AND FINALLY THE CITY DECIDED TO
PULL THE PLUG ON THE EVENTS AND IT ACTUALLY TOOK QUITE A
BIT OF WORK TO KILL CASTRO HALLOWEEN IN THE CASTRO BUT
THEY KILLED IT AND AND YET DESPITE ALL THAT THE SAN
DESPITE THE CELEBRATION HAVING LOST MUCH OF ITS QUEERNESS
AND MUCH OF ITS MAGIC IN THE FINAL YEARS FOND MEMORIES OF
HALLOWEEN IN THE CASTRO ENDURED AND PEOPLE KEPT SAYING YOU KNOW
COULDN'T WE DO SOMETHING? COULDN'T WE HAVE SOMETHING MORE
LIKE CASTRO HALLOWEEN AGAIN NOW IN 2000 IN 2020 THREE AND 2024
A SERIES OF SUCCESSFUL NIGHT MARKETS AROUND THE CITY
PROMPTED CASTRO COMMUNITY LEADERS TO CREATE ONE OF THEIR
OWN. AND THANKS TO THE HARD WORK
AND ENTHUSIASM OF THE CASTRO MERCHANTS, A SHOUT OUT TO TERRY
AUSTIN BENNETT AND JEN MEYER WHO WERE LEADING THE
ORGANIZATION AT THE TIME FUNDING FROM THE CIVIC JOY
FUND. HI MANNY.
AND PRODUCTION BY CG EVENTS. THE CASTRO LAUNCHED ITS FIRST
NIGHT MARKET IN OCTOBER OF 2024 AND THEY JUST GOT BETTER
AND BETTER EACH MONTH AFTER THAT AND AFTER THAT SERIES OF
SUCCESSFUL NIGHT MARKETS THERE WAS A HAPPY COINCIDENCE IN 2025
WITH HALLOWEEN FALLING ON A FRIDAY NIGHT.
>> SO THE GROUP GATHERED BEFORE YOU LED BY NATE BERG DREW FROM
THE EXPERIENCE WITH THE NIGHT MARKETS AND THAT SORT OF
NOSTALGIC FEELING THAT MAYBE WE COULD DO SOMETHING A LITTLE
MORE AMBITIOUS WITH OUR CASTRO HALLOWEENS TO CREATE THE FIRST
EVER CASTRO HALLOWEEN NIGHT MARKETS.
NOW I WILL ADMIT THAT WHEN SOME OF THESE FOLKS FIRST PRESENTED
THE IDEA OF REVIVING A CASTRO HALLOWEEN CELEBRATION BY
EXPANDING THE NIGHT MARKET TO ME I WAS SKEPTICAL.
>> I WAS CONCERNED AS I KNEW NEIGHBORS WERE CONCERNED.
I KNEW THE POLICE DEPARTMENT WAS CONCERNED.
THERE WAS A LOT OF CONCERN BUT THESE ORGANIZERS WOULD NOT
ALLOW MY CONCERN TO STIFLE THE FUN THEY ADDRESSED MY CONCERNS
AND THE CONCERNS OF THE POLICE DEPARTMENT AND THE CONCERNS OF
NEIGHBORS. THEY BROUGHT IN CASTRO
COMMUNITY ON PATROL. I WORKED WITH THE MTA, WORKED
WITH SFPD WHICH WAS A VERY IMPORTANT PARTNERSHIP TO ENSURE
THAT THE NEIGHBORHOOD REMAINS SAFE.
>> THAT NIGHT WE THEY HAD EXCELLENT PARTNERS IN THE CITY
TEAMING WITH KELLY VARIAN AND BEN VAN HOUTEN FROM THE
OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT WHO
HELPED BOTH WITH FUNDING AND WORKING ON LOGISTICS.
>> AND IN THE END THE 2020 FIVE CASTRO HALLOWEEN NIGHT MARKET
WAS AN INCREDIBLE SUCCESS DRAWING TENS OF THOUSANDS OF
VISITORS SAFELY. REVELERS AND FAMILIES THE NIGHT
WAS BRIMMING WITH LIVE MUSIC AND DAZZLING COSTUMES AND DRAG
PERFORMANCES BUT ALSO EMBRACED ITS ROOTS AS WITH FAMILY
FRIENDLY ACTIVITIES AND A FOCUS ON THE BUSINESSES THAT MAKE UP
THE CASTRO. >> IT WAS A GREAT JOYFUL,
VIBRANT NIGHT. SO TO BEN, THANK YOU FOR
WORKING ALONGSIDE THE ORGANIZERS.
TO GREG YEE, THANK YOU FOR WORKING WITH S.F. PD AND CASTRO
COMMITTEE ON PATROL IN YOUR CASE TO THE SFPD WHICH COULDN'T
BE WITH US HERE TODAY. THEY HAD I THINK MORE THAN 100
OFFICERS THAT NIGHT AVAILABLE IN CASE SOMETHING WENT WRONG.
THE SAFETY WAS WITH AS I SAID, WITHOUT EVER WITHOUT A DOUBT
EVERYONE'S BIGGEST CONCERN. BUT YOU ALL WORK TOGETHER TO
PATROL THE STREETS. YOU WORK CLOSELY WITH THE
MERCHANTS TO ENSURE THAT NEW REGULATIONS AROUND ALCOHOL
CONSUMPTION IN OUR ENTERTAINMENT ZONE WOULD BE
PROPERLY FOLLOWED. AND NATE, YOU WERE THE YOU
KNOW, THE INSTIGATOR DREAMER NEVER GIVE HER UP OR MANNY
NEIGHBOR BUT ALSO CIVIC JOY FUND FOUNDER HELPED FUND THE
EVENT COMFORT AND JOY SEAMLESSLY INTEGRATED THERE
GLOW OF THE STREET IN THE STREETS EVENT INTO THIS ONE
AND REVIVED SOME OF YOU KNOW I THINK WHAT I HAD SEEN IN THE
90S WHEN I SAW ALL THAT ART IN THOSE WINDOWS AND LOVED IT
SO MUCH AND CHRIS CARRINGTON AND GREG SARASOTA WELL WE HAVE
CHRIS LOWE FROM CG EVENTS YOU'VE JUST IT'S ALL OF THESE
EVENTS HAVE BEEN SO AMAZING. SO I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU ALL
FOR YOUR PERSISTENCE AND YOUR DETERMINATION TO KEEP THE
CASTRO FUN AND GAY AND HALLOWEEN 2025 WAS A GREAT
START AND I KNOW IT'S JUST GOING TO GET BETTER AND BETTER.
>> NATE THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MAN.
WOMAN AND THANK YOU, SUPERVISORS.
WHAT AN HONOR. IT'S GREAT TO BE HERE.
I DO HAVE TO CONFESS THOUGH ALL I DID WAS SEND A TEXT.
>> WHAT? WHEN I BECAME CASTRO MERCHANTS
PRESIDENT LAST YEAR PEOPLE OF COURSE STARTED ASKING ME ABOUT
THE BIG FESTIVALS YOU KNOW PRIDE WHAT ARE WE GOING TO DO
TO MAKE IT BIGGER? AND HALLOWEEN WAS THE OTHER ONE
AND OF COURSE AS PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN STATED, THAT'S A VERY
LOADED QUESTION WHEN YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT HALLOWEEN THERE'S
THE CRAZY PARTIES AND THE COMPLICATED MEMORIES YOU KNOW,
COMPLICATED TO SAY THE LEAST. SO IT WAS LAST SUMMER I SENT
THAT TEXT THAT I MENTIONED. OF COURSE I SENT IT TO MANNY
BECAUSE MANNY KNOWS EVERYBODY AND THEN ONE TEXT TURNED INTO
DOZENS AND THEN SUDDENLY EVERYBODY'S TALKING ABOUT IT.
IT LEAKS INTO THE PRESS AND THEN YOU KNOW, WE PUT THE
CART BEFORE THE HORSE I GUESS YOU WOULD SAY AND CONCERNS
STARTED BEING RAISED. SO NEXT THING WE KNOW WE WERE
AT THE POLICE STATION. WE WEREN'T UNDER ARREST BUT WE
WERE THERE FOR A MEETING. IT WAS A VERY PACKED CONFERENCE
ROOM. CHRIS CARRINGTON TO HIS GREAT
CREDIT WAS BEING GRILLED BY PUBLIC SAFETY OFFICIALS,
ESPECIALLY SOMEBODY FROM S.F. MTA.
I DON'T KNOW HOW HE GOT THROUGH IT BUT HE AMAZED ME THAT DAY.
HE WAS EXTREMELY POISED AND HAD DONE HIS HOMEWORK.
SO HUGE CREDIT TO CHRIS AND AND ALL THE WHILE I WAS THINKING,
YOU KNOW, ONE OF MY FAVORITE PEOPLE NANCY PELOSI ALWAYS SAID
DON'T AGONIZE, ORGANIZE. AND I HAVE A T-SHIRT THAT SAYS
THAT IT'S REALLY CUTE. IT'S PINK AND THAT'S WHAT WE
DID. WE GOT EVERYBODY INTO THE SAME
ROOM AND WE FIGURED IT OUT TOGETHER, YOU KNOW?
AND SO HALLOWEEN EVERYBODY BASICALLY WAS JUST ASKING THE
SAME VERY UNDERSTANDABLE QUESTION, RAFAEL IS CAN WE
BRING THIS BACK SAFELY AND TO THESE FOLKS CREDIT BEHIND ME WE
WE DID IT WAS AMAZING. BUT AGAIN, I DON'T TAKE THE
CREDIT. I SENT THAT ONE TEXT THAT
CREDIT BELONGS TO THE PEOPLE BEHIND ME AND OTHERS WHO ARE
NOT HERE INCLUDING OFFICER PANDOLFI FROM S.F. PD.
THEY HANDLED ALL THE DETAILS AND THEY MADE WHAT LOOKS THEY
MAY LOOK EFFORTLESS WHEN IT'S REALLY ANYTHING BUT EFFORTLESS
TO DO SOMETHING NOT THAT BIG. SO WE ALL GREATLY APPRECIATE
THE RECOGNITION. THANK YOU FOR BELIEVING IN THE
CASTRO. THANK YOU FOR BELIEVING IN OUR
COMMUNITY TO PULL THIS OFF PLEASE.
I KNOW YOU ALL AGREE WITH ME BUT LET'S REMEMBER THAT SAN
FRANCISCO SHINES BRIGHTEST WHEN WE INVEST IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS
AND OUR SMALL BUSINESSES. I'M DEEPLY HONORED TO BE HERE
TODAY. THANK YOU.
AND I THINK WE NEED TO DO HALLOWEEN AGAIN BUT IT'S ON A
SATURDAY THIS YEAR SO WE'LL HAVE TO PLAN FOR THAT.
>> THANK YOU AGAIN, A GREAT PLAYING A ROLE GOTHAM YEAH,
THAT'S RIGHT AND I THINK AND IT WAS WITH ALL RIGHT THANK YOU.
YEAH WITH APOLOGIES TO DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR ALAN HUANG I
SCREWED UP BUT IT IS YOUR THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG IT'S OKAY MR. PRESIDENT.
>> I LIKE JING MO TO COME UP. OKAY.
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN AND COLLEAGUES IT IS MY GREAT
HONOR TO RECOGNIZE JING MO ATHLETIC ASSOCIATION WHICH HAS
PLAYED AN IMPORTANT ROLE IN PRESERVING AND SHARING
CHINESE MARTIAL ARTS AND CULTURE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. JING MO TRACES ITS ROOTS TO THE
CHAN WU ATHLETIC ASSOCIATION FOUNDED IN SHANGHAI IN THE
EARLY 1900S BY YUN GAP WHO WAS PORTRAYED BY JET LI IN THE
MOVIE FEARLESS. THE ASSOCIATION WAS ALSO THE
SUBJECT OF THE BRUCE LEE FILM FIST OF FURY, WHOSE CANTONESE
TITLE IS JING MO MUN THE LEGACY OF JING MO WAS BROUGHT TO SAN
FRANCISCO IN THE EARLY 1960S BY GRANDMASTER WANG JACKMAN.
GRANDMASTER WANG WAS WIDELY KNOWN FOR HIS 1964 MATCH WITH
BRUCE LEE IN OAKLAND BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY HE DEVOTED DECADES
TO TEACHING MENTORING STUDENTS AND STRENGTHENING COMMUNITY
THROUGH DISCIPLINE, RESPECT AND CULTURAL PRIDE.
FOR NEARLY 40 YEARS JING MO HAS PARTNERED WITH THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC LIBRARY TO CELEBRATE LUNAR NEW YEAR
AND BRING CULTURAL PROGRAMING TO FAMILIES FROM OUR CITY
THROUGH MARTIAL ARTS DEMONSTRATIONS LAYING DANCE
AND EDUCATIONAL OUTREACH. THEY HAVE HELPED PASS DOWN
HERITAGE WHILE STRENGTHENING LITERACY AND YOUTH ENGAGEMENT.
I PERSONALLY WAS ABLE TO SEE THEIR LINE DANCE PERFORMANCES
AT THE SUNSET FARMERS MARKET AND BUILDING KIDS ONE OF OUR
LOCAL CHILDCARE CENTERS. >> AND THERE I WAS ABLE TO JUST
SEE HOW WELL YOU GUYS INTERACT WITH YOUR AUDIENCE FROM FROM
ADULTS TO LITTLE THREE YEAR OLDS TODAY UNDER THE LEADERSHIP
OF MASTER WING JING MO CONTINUES THAT MISSION HONORING
TRADITION WHILE SERVING THE PRESENT DAY COMMUNITY IN THE
SUNSET THEY ARE ESPECIALLY BELOVED PERFORMING AT
NEIGHBORHOOD SCHOOLS, FARMERS MARKETS, CULTURAL FESTIVALS
AND MOST RECENTLY AT THE SUNSET NIGHT MARKET.
IT ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL THAT WE PRESENT THE SPECIAL
COMMENDATIONS ON THE 15TH DAY OF LUNAR NEW YEAR A DAY THAT
MARKS THE CULMINATION OF CELEBRATION AND RENEWAL AND A
FITTING MOMENT TO HONOR JING MO'S ENDURING CONTRIBUTIONS
AND ACHIEVEMENTS. >> IT IS MY PLEASURE TO OFFER
THIS COMMENDATION TODAY. CONGRATULATIONS.
WE HAVE MEMBERS LILIAN E LILLIANA MCINNIS, KENRICK WONG
AND EVENTS DIRECTOR LORRAINE YI JOINING US HERE TODAY.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
AND YOU KNOW I, I HAVE TO THANK BECAUSE MOST OF THE TIME I HAVE
TO COME UP AND TELL EVERYONE YOU KNOW, WE ARE FAMOUS.
YOU DO KNOW THAT, RIGHT? BECAUSE IT'S TRUE.
OUR GRAND MASTER WONG JACKMAN IS THE MAN WHO FOUGHT BRUCE LEE
IN OAKLAND IN 1964 AND NOBODY KNOWS THAT.
>> BUT THE BIG THING IS HE DID NOT GET THE RECOGNITION HE
DESERVED. >> HE WAS A VERY HUMBLE MAN
AND HE PASSED ON EVERYTHING TO THE ONLY HEIR APPARENT, RIC
WANG, OUR MASTER NOW. AND YOU KNOW, WE HAVE SO MUCH
TO GIVE TO THE COMMUNITY WHAT BOTH OF THESE GENTLEMEN TAUGHT
US IS FIRST OF ALL LOVE FOR YOUR FAMILY, LOVE FOR YOUR
COMMUNITY AND MORE MORE THAN ANYTHING ELSE IS WHAT OUR
COMMUNITY HAS GIVEN US. >> SO YOU KNOW, WHEN YOU LOOK
AT US, WE ARE THE CHILDREN OF IMMIGRANTS.
>> SO WHAT DID THAT MEAN WHEN OUR PARENTS CAME TO THE UNITED
STATES AND YOU KNOW, WE WERE BORN HERE.
THEY WORKED SO HARD SO THEY WORKED HARD PUTTING A ROOF OVER
OUR HEADS AND FEEDING US BUT THEY COULD NOT HELP US WITH OUR
HOMEWORK. SO THEY SAID WHAT YOU NEED TO
DO IS GO TO THE LIBRARY. THE LIBRARIANS ARE WONDERFUL.
THEY WILL HELP YOU UNDERSTAND EVERYTHING YOU NEED TO KNOW.
AND IT WAS TRUE WE ALL WENT TO THE LIBRARIES.
WE LEARNED WONDERFUL THINGS FROM LIBRARIANS AND THEY SAID
YOU DON'T STOP HERE YOU THEN YOU GO TO SCHOOL AND YOU LEARN
EVERYTHING THE TEACHERS HAVE TO GIVE YOU.
>> AND WHAT DID THAT HAPPEN? WELL, WE ALL BECAME
PROFESSIONALS EVERY ONE OF OUR GROUP ALTHOUGH WE LOVE MARTIAL
ARTS, SPENT 30, 40, 50 YEARS PRACTICING WE ALL BECAME VERY
GOOD CAREER PROFESSIONALS. >> WE BECAME DOCTORS,
PROFESSORS OF ANY KIND OF EDUCATION.
YOU CAN THINK OF RADIOLOGY ALSO OUR OUR LEADER RIGHT NOW, RICK
WING IS A PROFESSOR OF MATH AT S.F. STATE UNIVERSITY.
WE HAVE CITY PLANNERS. WE HAVE TEACHERS OF RADIOLOGY.
>> WE HAVE EVERYTHING YOU CAN THINK OF.
BUT WHAT WE ALL AGREED IS WE HAVE TO THANK THESE LIBRARIANS.
WE HAVE TO THANK THE TEACHERS WHO DID ALL OF THAT FOR US.
>> SO WHAT WE DECIDED TO DO IS COMMIT OUR LIFE TO HELPING
PROMOTE LITERACY IN EDUCATION. SO FOR THE PAST 40 YEARS EVERY
YEAR WE GO TO THE SAN FRANCISCO LIBRARIES AND ALSO DON'T FORGET
PRESCHOOLS, HOSPITALS, SENIOR EVENTS AND EVERYTHING YOU CAN
THINK OF. >> BUT WITH THE YOUNGSTERS WE
GO THERE TO TELL THEM THE MOST IMPORTANT THING IN YOUR LIFE IS
EDUCATION. WHERE DO YOU GET IT?
YOU GO TO THE LIBRARY, YOUR HONOR, YOUR TEACHERS, YOU HONOR
YOUR PARENTS AND IF YOU DO THAT YOU WILL HAVE A VERY SUCCESSFUL
LIFE AND FOR EVERY SHOW WE DO EVEN THE PRESCHOOLERS WE SAY
THE SAME THING BECAUSE WE WANT TO BUILD THAT FOUNDATION THE
FOUNDATION WE GOT AND YOU KNOW ALL OF US WE WENT TO PUBLIC
SCHOOLS I'M SORRY WE DID NOT HAVE, YOU KNOW, EXTREMELY
WEALTHY PARENTS BUT SOMEHOW WE BECAME DOCTORS.
WE BECAME PROFESSORS OF MATH. WE BECAME, YOU KNOW, ENGINEERS.
WE BECAME ALL EVERYTHING YOU CAN THINK OF.
>> SO WHAT DID THAT MEAN? YES, WE TRY TO TEACH THE NEXT
GENERATION YOU CAN DO IT TO BE PROUD OF YOURSELF.
BE PROUD OF YOUR PARENTS. BE PROUD OF BEING AN IMMIGRANT
BUT ALSO BE A PROUD AMERICAN AND MAKE THE BEST OF YOUR LIFE.
>> SO FOR THE NEXT GENERATION ALL OF OUR KIDS GUESS WHAT THEY
ARE THEIR DOCTORS, THEIR TEACHERS, MY DAUGHTERS.
I'M LUCKY TO HAVE ONE HERE. BOTH MY DAUGHTERS ARE IN THE
HEALTH CARE INDUSTRY. THEY TEACH AND THEY THEY TREAT
CANCER BUT THEY STILL DO ALL THE MARTIAL ARTS WITH US AND WE
JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE EVERYONE KNOWS THIS LEGACY WILL CONTINUE
AS LONG AS WE BREATHE BECAUSE WE LOVE OUR LIBRARIANS, WE LOVE
OUR TEACHERS, WE LOVE OUR COMMUNITY AND WE WANT TO MAKE
SURE THAT ALL THE GOOD THINGS WE HAVE TO OFFER CONTINUE ON.
>> SO JAYMA WILL ALWAYS BE HERE AND I HAVE THESE WONDERFUL
PEOPLE BEHIND ME. I'M SORRY WE HAVE WE WANTED TO
HAVE MORE PEOPLE LIKE A CROWD THAT WAS THERE BEFORE BUT YOU
KNOW THEY ALL WORK. WE HAVE A LOT OF PEOPLE IN LAW
ENFORCEMENT, DOJ, EVERYTHING YOU CAN THINK OF THAT WE ARE SO
HAPPY TO BE HERE AND WE ARE SO PLEASED TO BE IN FRONT OF YOU.
I WAS THE FIRST CHINESE WOMAN ADVERTISING MANAGER FOR THE SAN
FRANCISCO CHRONICLE. I'VE SPOKEN IN FRONT OF
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE AND I WILL TELL YOU THIS IS THE ONLY TIME
IN MY LIFE I HAVE A LUMP IN MY THROAT.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. GOD BLESS YOU.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT
. ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S
GO BACK TO ROLL CALL. >> NEXT UP TO INTRODUCE NEW
BUSINESS IS SUPERVISOR WALTON SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG WONG IS NOT
IN THE CHAMBER. SUPERVISOR CHAN SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT, SUPERVISOR HUANG.
YEAH. OKAY.
APOLOGIES AGAIN, SUPERVISOR WONG.
NO WORRIES. UM, SCROLLING DOWN TO MY ROLL
CALL NOTES. OKAY, COLLEAGUES, TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING THE IMPORTANCE OF
THE JUNIOR RESERVE OFFICER TRAINING CORPS PROGRAM JROTC
AND ENCOURAGING THE SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL
DISTRICT TO CONTINUE PROVIDING HIGH SCHOOL STUDENTS THE
OPPORTUNITY TO TO PARTICIPATE AND TO ENSURE THE PROGRAM IS
PRESERVED AS CURRENTLY CONSTITUTED.
JROTC HAS BEEN PART OF SFD FOR MORE THAN 90 YEARS.
IT IS CURRENTLY OFFERED AT SIX HIGH SCHOOLS AND SERVES MORE
THAN 900 ENROLLED CADETS ALONG WITH HUNDREDS OF ADDITIONAL
STUDENTS THROUGH PHYSICAL EDUCATION.
INDEPENDENT STUDY FOR MANY YOUNG PEOPLE ACROSS OUR CITY.
THIS IS NOT JUST AN ELECTIVE. IT IS A MEANINGFUL PART OF
THEIR HIGH SCHOOL EXPERIENCE. THE PROGRAM TEACHES LEADERSHIP
COMMUNICATION, SELF-AWARENESS, FIRST AID, CONFLICT MANAGEMENT
SERVICE LEARNING, PHYSICAL TRAINING AND CIVIC EDUCATION.
IT FULFILLS COLLEGE PREPARATORY REQUIREMENTS AND HELPS STUDENTS
BUILD SKILLS THAT WILL SERVE THEM LONG AFTER GRADUATION.
CADETS COLLECTIVELY COMPLETE TENS OF THOUSANDS OF COMMUNITY
SERVICE HOURS EACH YEAR AND REGULARLY EARN NATIONAL
RECOGNITION. WHAT STANDS OUT MOST TO ME IS
WHAT STUDENTS SAY ABOUT THE PROGRAM.
THEY DESCRIBE JROTC AS A SECOND FAMILY.
THEY TALK ABOUT FINDING CONFIDENCE STRUCTURE
AND BELONGING. THOSE ARE OUTCOMES THAT MATTER
IN EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD AND EVERY SCHOOL.
IN 2008 THE SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS APPROVED PROPOSITION V
DECLARING IT CITY POLICY THAT JROTC CONTINUE TO BE AVAILABLE
IN S.F. U.S. HIGH SCHOOLS. IN RECENT YEARS ENROLLMENT HAS
GROWN SIGNIFICANTLY, REFLECTING CONTINUED INTEREST AND SUPPORT
FROM STUDENTS AND FAMILIES. THIS RESOLUTION IS ABOUT
RECOGNIZING A PROGRAM WITH A LONG HISTORY IN OUR CITY
AND AFFIRMING THE VALUE IT PROVIDES TO OUR STUDENTS.
IT IS ABOUT SUPPORTING STUDENT CHOICE AND PRESERVING
OPPORTUNITIES THAT FOSTER LEADERSHIP RESPONSIBILITY
AND CIVIC ENGAGEMENT. I'M ALSO INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION URGING THE GOVERNOR AND THE STATE LEGISLATURE TO
REJECT PROPOSED CUTS TO MEDI-CAL DENTAL AND TO FULLY
RESTORE AND PROTECT FUNDING FOR CHILDREN'S DENTAL CARE IN THE
STATE BUDGETS. I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUES
SUPERVISORS SUTTER, CHERYL WALTON CHEN AND FIELDER FOR
THEIR CO-SPONSORSHIP. AND AS SOMEBODY THAT USED TO
WORK IN SEIU, H.W. MEDI-CAL HAS SUCH AN IMPORTANT IMPACT TO
PATIENT PATIENT CARE AND OUR HOSPITAL STAY ABILITY OF OUR
HOSPITAL SYSTEM. THIS RESOLUTION IS ABOUT A VERY
BASIC PRINCIPLE. DENTAL CARE IS HEALTH CARE.
PREVENTATIVE DENTAL CARE HELPS KEEP KIDS HEALTHY IN SCHOOL
AND OUT OF EMERGENCY ROOMS. WHEN CHILDREN DON'T GET CARE,
THE CONSEQUENCES ARE SERIOUS. PAIN IN ACTION, DIFFICULTY
EATING MISSED SCHOOL AND AVOIDABLE LONG TERM HEALTH
CARE PROBLEMS. IN SAN FRANCISCO, NEARLY 1 IN 3
CHILDREN RELIES ON MEDI-CAL FOR HEALTH COVERAGE.
SO MEDICAL DENTAL IS A CRITICAL PART OF OUR HEALTH CARE SAFETY
NET. WE ALSO KNOW THAT ORAL HEALTH
DISPARITIES ARE REAL AND PERSISTENT.
LOW INCOME CHILDREN AND CHILDREN OF COLOR FACE
HIGHER RATES OF TOOTH DECAY. AND THOSE DISPARITIES SHOW UP
EARLY. THE PROPOSED STATE BUDGET CUT
WOULD REDUCE MEDI-CAL DENTAL FUNDING FOR CHILDREN BY $144
MILLION AND WOULD ALSO FORFEIT APPROXIMATELY 182 MILLION
IN MATCHING FEDERAL FUNDS. AND ALL OF THIS IS BEING
PROPOSED FOR A SAVINGS THAT REPRESENTS A TINY FRACTION OF
THE OVERALL STATE BUDGET BOTH OUTSIZED CONSEQUENCES FOR
CHILDREN AND FAMILIES. CUTS TO PREVENTIVE TIVE CARE DO
NOT ELIMINATE COSTS. THEY SHIFT COSTS LATER AND TO
MORE EXPENSIVE EMERGENCY AND ACUTE CARE SETTINGS.
THIS IS BAD FOR KIDS, BAD FOR FAMILIES AND BAD PUBLIC POLICY.
BUDGETS ARE A REFLECTION OF PRIORITIES.
THIS RESOLUTION MAKES CLEAR THAT SAN FRANCISCO BELIEVES
PROTECTING CHILDREN'S ACCESS TO BASIC HEALTH CARE, INCLUDING
DENTAL CARE MUST REMAIN A PRIORITY.
>> THEIR ASSESSMENT AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
PUBLIC COMMENT. AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES
YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT. PLEASE LINE UP TO YOUR RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER ALONG THE CURTAINS.
YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED ON WHETHER OR NOT THE
BOARD SHOULD ENTER INTO CLOSED SESSION THE MATTER CONTAINED
IN ITEM 42 FOR THE PURPOSE OF CONFERRING WITH OR RECEIVING
ADVICE FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY REGARDING EXISTING LEGISLATIVE
LITIGATION ITEMS 43 THROUGH 55 THE ITEMS ON THE FLOOR ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA.
GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT MUST BE
WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
ALL OTHER AGENDA COMMENT WILL HAVE BEEN REPORTED OUT TO THE
BOARD BY AN APPROPRIATE COMMITTEE WHERE THE PUBLIC
COMMENT REQUIREMENT OCCURRED. >> WELCOME TO THE FIRST
SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS SCOTT FEENEY. I'M A MISSION DISTRICT
RESIDENT. I'M HERE TO SPEAK TO 2020
PROPOSITION II WHICH RAISE THE TRANSFER TAX ON HIGH VALUED
REAL ESTATE OVER $10 MILLION TO FUND SOCIAL HOUSING.
IN JANUARY I ASKED YOU TO STAND BY PROP I AND TO DEDICATE THE
FUNDS TO THEIR INTENDED PURPOSE OF BUILDING SOCIAL HOUSING.
SO I WAS DISMAYED TO LEARN LAST WEEK THAT THREE OF YOU ARE
SPONSORING AN ORDINANCE TO INSTEAD REPEAL PROP I.
>> SUCH A REPEAL MAKES NO SENSE FROM THE STANDPOINT OF BUILDING
HOUSING PROP I TAXES MOSTLY OFFICE BUILDINGS INCLUDING THE
TRUMP OWNED 555 CALIFORNIA WHICH IS CURRENTLY BEING
SHOPPED AROUND AND THAT SALE ALONE WOULD GET A $45 MILLION
TAX BREAK OR THIS REPEAL TO GO THROUGH OVERALL PROP II IS
EXPECTED TO GENERATE ON THE ORDER OF $100 MILLION A YEAR
IN THE NEXT COUPLE OF YEARS. IT'S BEEN ASSERTED THAT A
REPEAL COULD BE REVENUE NEUTRAL BECAUSE OF A POTENTIAL BALLOT
MEASURE BUT IT'S NOT CLEAR IF SUCH BALLOT MEASURE IS EVEN
LEGAL LET ALONE POLITICALLY FEASIBLE AND WE SIMPLY DON'T
HAVE ENOUGH FORECLOSURES IN THE CITY FOR THAT TO MAKE UP $100
MILLION A YEAR REPEALING PROP I WOULD OVERTURN THE WILL OF THE
VOTERS WHO APPROVED PROP EIGHT BY 15 POINTS CITYWIDE IN ONE OF
THE REPEAL SPONSORS DISTRICTS PROP I ACTUALLY WON 65% OF THE
VOTE WHICH FOR REFERENCE IS GREATER THAN THE 63% NO VOTE
FOR SUNSET DUNES IN DISTRICT FOR WHICH THEY RECORD THEIR
SUPERVISOR OVER. >> WE CANNOT AFFORD TO GIVE A
100 MILLION DOLLAR A YEAR TAX BREAK TO RICH REAL ESTATE
INVESTORS LIKE DONALD TRUMP WHEN THE CITY HAS A BUDGET
DEFICIT AND AN AFFORDABLE HOUSING SHORTAGE CUTTING OFF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING FUNDS IS NIMBYISM BY OTHER MEANS.
IT STOPS HOUSING FROM GETTING BUILT AND I ONCE AGAIN ASK THIS
BOARD NOT TO REPEAL PROP I BUT INSTEAD TO DEVOTE THE FUNDS TO
THEIR INTENDED PURPOSE OF BUILDING SOCIAL HOUSING.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HEY, HOW'S EVERYONE DOING THIS MARCH THERE?
>> MY NAME IS EAST WASHINGTON AND I'M THE FILLMORE
QUARTERMASTER. SO LET ME JUST START OFF BY
DOING SOME HISTORY. MOST OF Y'ALL AROUND HERE BOARD
SUPERVISED IN THIS CITY AC WAY BEFORE ALL THE THE I THINK THE
ONLY ONE WAS AROUND WHEN I STARTED WAS THE CLERKS.
>> SO THAT GOES BACK 20 SOME YEARS 30 40 SOME YEARS TO HOW I
LOOK AT IT. >> I'VE BEEN A CITY HALL ALL
THESE YEARS. BUT WHAT I'M HERE TO TALK ABOUT
IS THE WEST. >> IN ADDITION WE ARE IN A
CRISIS RIGHT NOW DEALING FROM THE JIM JONES SITUATION ON GARY
TO ALL OF THE NEW DEVELOPMENT THAT ARE HAPPENING IN THE
FILLMORE. >> WE GOT WE GOT REPARATIONS OF
COURSE WE'VE GOT THE DREAM KEEPERS SITUATION.
>> WE GOT YOSHI SAFEWAY, WEST BAY, L.A. HEAL HUTCH BUCHANAN
MALL. AND I GOT TO SIT DOWN WITH THE
MAYOR. CAN I SIT DOWN WITH HIM YET?
WE GOT A PLAZA EAT MARTIN LUTHER KING WE GOT A FREE U.S.
BILLION DOLLAR PROJECT GOING. WE'VE GOT THOMAS PAINE.
HE'S BILLY THE GARY STREET. >> WE GOT THE MALL UP
AND THERE'S SO MANY THINGS THAT COULD GO ON AND MY TIME WILL
PERMIT BUT WE MUST ADDRESS THAT.
I'M HERE TO SAY IT'S ONLY TWO BLACKS, THREE BLACKS IN HERE,
ME THE SUPERVISOR OVER THERE. BUT THAT GOES ON A PERCENTAGE
OF WHAT'S HAPPENING HERE IN THE CITY.
BUT I'M NOT GOING TO LET OUR HISTORY LEGACY DIE.
>> MY NAME IS ASIAN. I'M ON THE CASE.
I'M THE FILLMORE CORRIDOR AMBASSADOR SO FITSUM RESPECT
DON'T THAT NAME. >> YEAH.
SO I'M JUST SAYING I'M LIVE AND DIRECT ON MY CHANNEL BUT I
JUST HAD TO COME IN AND TELL YOU THE PROBLEMS THAT WE GOT
IN THE WEST INITIATIVE. >> WE'RE GOING TO ADDRESS THOSE
ISSUES THAT I GOT TO SIT DOWN WITH THE MAYOR.
I KNOW HE'S A CARE I KNOW HE CARE.
BUT I DO ALSO KNOW HE'S A BILLIONAIRE.
>> I LIVE IN DIRECT. YOU DON'T HAVE TO JUST YOU'LL
SAY THANK YOU MR. WASHINGTON. >> CAN WE HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE? THAT'S A REALLY HARD ACT TO
FOLLOW. BUT ANYWAY, I'M HERE ON A
TYPICAL THING TO TALK ABOUT CORRUPTION IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND THE LATEST THING WITH THE UP AND THE POLICE DEPARTMENT
AND THEY RUN A SUPPOSEDLY TIGHT ORGANIZATION DOWN IN THE DOWN
AND AT THE BAY NEAR CHIEFS STADIUM AND FOR SOME REASON THE
HEAD OF THE THE SO CALLED INTELLIGENCE DEPARTMENT FOR THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT HAS NOT FOLLOWED HIS OWN RULES AND THE
RULES OF THE CITY. AND AGAIN, WE'RE CAUGHT IN A
SITUATION WHERE WE ARE LOOKING LIKE WE HAVE DOUBLE PAID FOR A
COMPUTER STYLE CONTROL ACT WITH THE CITY INSTEAD OF GOING WITH
MOTOROLA, WE'RE GOING WITH A FAILED FAVORITE INSIDER OF
SOMEBODY AND THIS IS OCCURRING FREQUENTLY.
I'M LOOK AT THE APP WHAT HAPPENED WITH THE MAYOR'S
SELECTION OF HIS OWN PERSONAL COMPUTER ORGANIZATION WHICH
PROBABLY COSTS TWICE AS MUCH AS WHAT THE LET NEXT COMPETING
PARTY OFFERED. WELL THAT'S THAT'S ON THE
MAYOR'S SIDE. THIS IS ON THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AS A SIDE BECAUSE SOMEHOW THEY'VE AVOIDED
SUPERVISION BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS BECAUSE THEY PUT
IN A CONTRACT BID FOR $9,000,999 INSTEAD OF 10
MILLION WHICH WOULD HAVE REQUIRED THE CONTRACT TO GO TO
BEFORE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
SO YOU GUYS HAVE GOT TO GET HOLD OF THIS.
IT'S HAPPENED EVER SINCE WILLIE BROWN UP WHAT I WOULD APPOINT
CRONIES TO RUN A COMPUTER DEPARTMENT THAT THEY HAD NO
EXPERIENCE LIKE IT'S HAPPENING ALL OVER AGAIN THANKS FOR THANK
YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
HI MY NAME IS RICHARD JOHNSON AND I'M HERE TO SPEAK ABOUT THE
HAYES STREET CLOSURE I THINK THIS IS MY THIRD TIME IS
SPEAKING IN FRONT OF THE BOARD .
I HAVE SPOKE VERY CLEARLY IN FRONT OF THE S.F. MTA
AND THE REASON I'M SPEAKING TO YOU TODAY IS BECAUSE THIS WAS
SOMETHING THAT WAS CREATED IN THE BOARD BUT IT WAS CREATED
IN SUCH A FASHION WHERE THERE'S NO APPEAL PROCESS FOR THE
CITIZENS ARE ONLY APPEAL IS THROUGH THE S.F. MTA BOARD
WHICH WE ARE ON WEEK 64 OF DOCUMENTED VIOLATIONS OF WHERE
THEY HAVE DONE MANY THINGS WRONG AND AT THIS POINT NOT
ONLY IS THE CITY LOSING MONEY BUT WE AS A GROUP HAVE ACTUALLY
ONE OF OUR MEMBERS HAS BEEN THREATENED WITH LEGAL ACTION
BECAUSE WE HAVE BEEN FORCED TO DOCUMENT THESE ISSUES.
SO I COME TO YOU AS THE PEOPLE'S HOUSE BECAUSE THIS
NEEDS TO BE TAKEN CARE OF A PROPER EVERY OTHER MEANS AS A
APPEAL PROCESS TO IT AND IN THIS CASE IS WHERE WE ARE KIND
OF REVOLVED IN A CIRCLE OF GOING AROUND WE'RE DEPENDING
UPON OUR SUPERVISOR WHO HAS TURNED A BLIND EYE TO US
AND WILL NOT LISTEN TO US. THAT COMES BACK TO YOU AS A
GROUP WHERE WE HAVE TRIED TO APPEAL BEFORE THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AND WE ARE STUCK IN THIS CYCLE OF WHAT DOES YOUR
SUPERVISOR FEEL ABOUT THIS? SO WE ARE UP AGAINST THE WALL
WITH WHAT WE ARE EXPECTED TO DO AND I'M COMING TO YOU TO CREATE
A PROPER APPEAL PROCESS WHERE EQUITY CAN ABIDE INSTEAD OF
POLITICS RULING THE DAY SO PLEASE LOOK TOWARDS A SOLUTION
TOWARDS A VERY POLITICAL AND A AND ESPECIALLY IN THE TIME
WHERE WE HAVE TIGHT BUDGETS WHERE THIS IS NOT MAKING MONEY
FOR THIS CITY WE ARE SPENDING. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
APOLOGIES FOR CUTTING YOU OFF. >> EVERYONE IS RECEIVING TWO
MINUTES TODAY. NEXT SPEAKER I'M TAKING STOCK
OF MY COMPLICITY AS AN AMERICAN YOURS AS THE AMERICAN
GOVERNMENT AND AMERICANS IN GENERAL AS AMERICA BUILDS
REQUIRES MORE WAREHOUSES TO STORE ABDUCTED PEOPLE
AND CHILDREN AS AMERICA BURIES INDIGENOUS AND BLACK HISTORY
AND EQUITY PROGRAMS MEANT TO BEGIN BALANCING THE SCALES WITH
THEIR WHITE CLASSMATES, COWORKERS AND COLLEAGUES AS
AMERICA STRIPS MORE RIGHTS FROM TRANS PEOPLE, KANSAS ESCALATING
STATE VIOLENCE ENACTED BY GOVERNMENT REPRESENTATIVES
AND STRIPPING TRANS PEOPLE OF THEIR DRIVER'S LICENSE IF IT
MATCHES THEIR GENDER AS AMERICA FIRES BLACK WOMEN FROM THEIR
JOBS AND INCREASED ALARMING RATES AND WHITE CHRISTIAN
INFLUENCERS RISE IN POPULARITY AS AMERICA'S AIYE SPREADS
THEIR WHITE SUPREMACIST MISOGYNISTIC PEDOPHILIC WEAPONS
INTO EVERY SECTOR OF OUR TECHNOLOGY, OF OUR EDUCATION,
OF OUR LIVES KILLING OUR ONLY ENVIRONMENT TO FEEL ITS TROJAN
HATE FILLED HORSE AS AMERICA STRIPS HEALTH CARE FROM
IMPOVERISHED PEOPLE AND IMMIGRANTS, GETTING THE CDC
AND PUBLIC HEALTH IN GENERAL INCLUDING OUR MAYOR AT LEAST
$40 MILLION FOR US TO CUT FROM OUR DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
. >> I'M JUST WONDERING HOW MANY
OF YOU ARE GOING TO RUBBER STAMP THAT MURDEROUS BUDGET AS
AMERICA ABDUCTS VENEZUELA'S PRESIDENT AND HIS WIFE AND THE
PRESS MOVES ON AS AMERICA KILLS DOZENS OF PEOPLE IN THE
CARIBBEAN WATERS AND WITH NARY A PROTEST AS AMERICA CREATES A
CORRUPT FALSE BOARD OF PEACE TO LEGITIMATELY COLONIZE PALESTINE
AND PALESTINIANS CONTINUE TO BE MURDERED AND TORTURED AS
AMERICAN ISRAEL SUCCESSFULLY CARRY OUT TWO REMOTE CONTROLLED
GENOCIDE PROBABLY SEMI-AUTONOMOUS YOU LOVE
AUTONOMY AUTONOMOUS LIKE THAT DON'T YOU?
AIN'T ANCIENT AND GAZA AND TRYING TO DO THE SAME WITH
ANY OTHER COUNTRY UNLESS THEY BEND BERNIE AS AMERICA RUN BY
RAPISTS AND WANT TO BE LITERAL ENSLAVERS AND PEDOPHILES
CARRIES OUT THAT THREAT WITH IRAN LET ALONE SHOULDN'T THAT
ALONE CAUSE AMERICANS OR ANY HUMAN BEING TO REVOLT?
INSTEAD YOU CONTINUE TO IGNORE YOUR CONSTITUENTS.
ARE WE NOT REVOLTED BY THIS? IS THIS NOT REVOLTING ENOUGH?
>> YEAH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. BOARD OF SUPERVISOR AND MAYOR
OFFICE OF SAN FRANCISCO THE TITLE OF THIS SPEECH IS WHY NOT
THE YEAR WAS 2002 AS A JOB INTERVIEW FOR KONO WHERE THE
FINAL AGREEMENT WAS I HAD TO WORK FOR NO PAY FOR SHORT
PERIOD TIME SO I WORKED. EVENTUALLY I GOT INTO
INVESTMENT SERIES A, SERIES B AND SERIES C I FUNDED THE CORE
TEAM IN THE CITY OF KONO WHERE MARTIN GRANT WHO HAPPENS TO BE
THE ARCHITECT OF NETSCAPE, THE YEAR WAS 2007.
MY DAYS OF OKINAWA WAS NUMBERED .
I STUCK WITH IT TO THE VERY END.
A YEAR EARLIER I WAS IN TOASTMASTER MEETING A
THOUGHT CEDED TO HIM I'D BE A SINGER.
>> WHY NOT? I WOKE UP A BIT LATER ONE
MORNING AND DECIDED TO BECOME A SINGER SO I LAND A JOB IN SIX
FLAGS AND I MOONLIGHTED WHILE WORKING IN IN KONO WHERE SO MY
QUESTION IS WHY NOT WHY NOT JUST ME BE THE ONE CRAZY GUY
WHO'S GOING TO DRAFT THE NEXT CONSTITUTION FOR HUMANITY
AND JOE BIDEN? WHY NOT ME?
WHY NOT? IT'S A LOT OF PEOPLE HERE IN A
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN THIS CHAMBER RIGHT HERE.
>> WHY NOT OWN IT? WHY NOT PUT THIS CONSTITUTION
IN A MAIDEN NAME NEXT TO STORE IN UNION SQUARE?
>> WHY NOT THAT POSSIBILITY AS AND AS IF WE CAN CREATE IT WE
CAN OWN IT AND SO ACCORDING TO TONY ROBBINS, HE WAS A DO NOT
REACT INSTEAD CHOOSE ALSO MYRON GORDON SIT SEE DO HALF THAT'S
ALL I HAVE TO SAY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER HI MY NAME IS
BRIAN STORE. >> I'M HERE TO TALK TO YOU GUYS
AGAIN ABOUT THE GENESIS EL RAD. 950 NEXT HE'S BEING USED OUT OF
COMPLIANCE. THEY CONTINUE TO RUN MILITARY
PROGRAM ON THE EL RISE TO AFFORD THEM THE ABILITY TO USE
THEM AS MILITARY WEAPONS. THAT'S THE FACTS.
THEY CONTINUE TO BE MISUSED AND USED AS A MILITARY WEAPON
OVER AND OVER AND OVER SINCE AUGUST WHEN I FIRST CAME HERE,
EVERY TIME I'VE SPOKE TO YOU GUYS THEY'VE CONTINUE TO BE
USED OUT OF COMPLIANCE. >> IT'S OUT OF CONTROL.
THESE GUYS ARE LAWLESS. THEY SHOULD NOT BE ALLOWED TO
BE ON L ROADS. THEY HAVE TOTAL DISREGARD FOR
PEOPLE'S SAFETY ANYWHERE THEY CAN TOUCH AN L READ PEOPLE'S
LIVES ARE IN DANGER. IT'S A FACT.
IT'S NOT A JOKE. THESE GUYS NEED TO BE TAKEN OFF
THE L ROADS IN SOUTHERN OREGON. THEY'RE OUT OF CONTROL.
IT'S BEEN THIS WAY FOR OVER THREE YEARS.
THREE YEARS? IT'S NOT ABOUT AUDIO TRACKING
AT ALL. IT'S ABOUT THE SETTINGS, THE
MILITARY SETTINGS ARE RUNNING ON L ROADS.
THEY CONTINUE TO NOT ONLY ME BUT I HAVE FOUR KIDS UNDER THE
AGE OF 12 THAT THEY CONTINUE TO DO THE SAME THING TO AUTO
TRACKED AND USE THE WEAPONS SETTINGS ON.
>> I URGE YOU GUYS TO DO A COMPLIANCE CHECK ON THE L RADS
ANY L RAD THAT CAN TOUCH SAN FRANCISCO WITHIN 55 MILES 55
MILES THAT'S THE RANGE ON THE L ROADS WHEN THEY WERE RUNNING
THESE WEAPON PROGRAMS. >> I APPRECIATE YOUR GUYS'S
TIME. I WANTED TO PUT A LITTLE BIT ON
THE RECORD HERE IF I'M ABLE TO GO ON WILL BE UP TO GET IT YOU
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS NEXT SPEAKER I'M A FORKLIFT
DRIVER IS IS THAT A PROFESSION AND I'M A PROFESSIONAL.
>> YOU KNOW I THINK THAT WHEN THE THE VOTING PROCESS THE
ELECTION PROCESS OBVIOUSLY SOME CERTAIN KINDS OF PEOPLE ARE
GOING TO MAKE IT INTO PUBLIC OFFICE ALTHOUGH WITH THE
DISTRICT ELECTIONS WE HAVE A LITTLE MORE VARIETY NONETHELESS
,YOU KNOW, YOU GOT TO HAVE THE MONEY.
IT'S PRETTY DIFFICULT. WHERE DOES THE MONEY COME FROM
? >> BUT THERE IS I JUST LEARNED
I WAS ON THE JURY AND I JUST LEARNED THERE'S THIS OTHER
OPTION CALLED THE CIVIL GRAND JURY AND YOU KNOW, I'M MULLING
IT BUT I HAVE TO SAY THAT WHEN I LOOK OVER THE FORM, YOU KNOW,
THERE'S A LOT OF PEOPLE AREN'T GOING TO QUALIFY FOR THIS
EITHER. AND YOU KNOW, I DON'T KNOW WHAT
THE YOU KNOW WHAT THE SILVER BULLET IS TO KIND OF GET PEOPLE
TO BE THINKING ABOUT THE REALITY THAT WE'RE IN RIGHT
NOW. >> YOU KNOW, AS MUCH AS I
APPRECIATE AFFORDABLE HOUSING ALL THE CAUSES THAT COME UP
HERE, THERE'S A LITTLE BIT OF A BIGGER ISSUE.
YOU KNOW, I JUST SAW A I SAW DENNIS HERRERA AND I DIDN'T
KNOW WHAT ELSE TO SAY TO HIM SO HE SEEMED DOWNTRODDEN SO I
DIDN'T KNOW WHAT TO SAY TO HIM. SO I SAID HEY, YOU HAVEN'T BEEN
INDICTED YET. >> SO I KNOW I'M SURE THAT
ISN'T THE RIGHT THING. BUT ONE OF THE THINGS I NOTICE
IS THAT THE PROJECTIONS, THE REPORTS THAT COME OUT ABOUT OUR
EMISSIONS THEY'RE ALWAYS SO ROSY.
THEY'RE LIKE WE'RE CUTTING DOWN ON EMISSIONS AND I KNOW THERE'S
A WHOLE BUNCH OF STUFF THAT THEY'RE LEAVING OUT BECAUSE
THAT'S OBVIOUSLY WE'RE NOT CUTTING DOWN ON EMISSIONS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. GOT TIME FOR ONE MORE?
>> SURE. OH, SORRY I JUST RAN HERE.
>> COULD YOU PUT UP THE PROJECTOR AS A GOV TV PLEASE?
THANK YOU. I'M HERE REPRESENTING SAN
FRANCISCANS FOR SOCIAL HOUSING .
I DON'T HAVE MUCH IN THE WAY OF PREPARED REMARKS BUT I'D LIKE
TO USE THIS TIME TO LIST OFF NAMES OF THE CLOSE TO 1000
PEOPLE THAT HAVE SIGNED ONTO A PETITION THAT ARE ASKING YOU TO
USE PROPERTY MONEY FOR WHAT WE WERE TOLD IT WAS GOING TO GO TO
WHICH IS A SOCIAL HOUSING PROGRAM.
I HAVE THE NAMES SOMEWHERE IN HERE.
>> WHO ARE YOU? HOW?
>> OH PLEASE I THEIR OPPOSE OR AMEND THE BILL THAT WHERE IS IT
? I'M REALLY SORRY I HAD TO RUN
HERE I CAN SAY MY MY NAME WAS ON THE FIRST SHEET.
THERE YOU GO HONEST B SHELLEY P LUKE OH SAMMY B OZONE F
BENJAMIN B ANDREA G THING DOESN'T REALLY ZOOM OUT MUCH
DOES A WALTER O'DANIEL G I G LEO Y DOMINGO D JOHN M DELANEY
H RABINOW MAHAL M RYAN R W H ZACHARY W MARTY DIEDRICH NADIA
STEPHEN M CALLING US ANDREW Z WE'RE ALL ASKING YOU TO USE
PROPERTY FUNDS FOR SOCIAL HOUSING.
WE JUST VOTED ON IT FIVE YEARS AGO AND WE HAD TO LEARN LAST
WEEK THAT THERE'S AN EFFORT NOT JUST TO PATCH THE NARROW THING
THAT APPLIES TO NEW PROJECTS BUT ALL THE REAL ESTATE
TRANSFER TAXES. >> THANK YOU.
HONEST. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD FOR GENERAL
PUBLIC COMMENT? ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> OH, I'M SORRY, SUPERGIRL. I THINK WE GOT SUPERGIRL.
COME ON UP. >> OH, I WASN'T THE LAST ONE.
SHE WAS KEEPING US WAITING FOR SUPERGIRL.
>> THANK YOU FOR WAITING, SUPERGIRL SURE.
GIVE ME A MINUTE HERE TO GET READY.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. OKAY, GREAT.
>> I FIRST I LIKE TO HI. I'M THE SUPERGIRL OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND I'D LIKE TO WISH EVERYONE A HAPPY NEW YEAR.
AND I DO THINK THE BOARD IS SUPERVISED.
THERE'S THE CLERK, THE MAYOR AND CFO OF T V HELLO FOR
THE OPPORTUNITY TO EXERCISE MY FIRST AMENDMENT RIGHT.
>> IT IS VITAL THAT WE CAN SPEAK FREELY IN THIS COUNTRY.
SO TODAY I WANT TO GRIEVANCE MY GOVERNMENT AND I HAVE A
QUESTION WHY DOES DONALD TRUMP CALL US THE ENEMY?
I WAS NEVER ANYONE'S ENEMY. I HAVE NOTHING BUT LOVE,
RESPECT AND UNDERSTANDING FOR MY FELLOW AMERICANS.
>> I DON'T SEE ANYONE ON THE EARTH AS MY ENEMY.
HE SPENT THE LAST TEN YEARS TELLING EVERYONE THAT PEOPLE
LIKE ME, LIKE US ARE THE ENEMY .
HE EVEN CALLED ONE OF HIS OWN APPARENTLY MARJORIE TAYLOR
GREENE A TRAITOR FOR ASKING FOR TRANSPARENCY ABOUT THE ARNSTEIN
FILES. I DISAGREE WITH HER ON MANY
THINGS BUT CALLING FOR TRANSPARENCY IS NOT TREASON.
>> IT DISTURBS ME THAT YOU DO THIS, MR. PRESIDENT.
THIS IS CAUSING AMERICA PAIN. >> YOU'RE SENDING BOMBS TO IRAN
ICE IS MURDERING INNOCENT CIVILIANS.
YES. YOU TOOK OUT THE REGIME BUT YOU
ALSO HELPED TO KILL SCHOOLCHILDREN.
NOW SOLDIERS ARE DYING IN AN ILLEGAL WAR NOT APPROVED BY
CONGRESS. >> WHERE IS THE PEACE AND UNITY
THAT YOU SPOKE OF? >> WHERE IS IT?
THANK YOU FOR YOUR ATTENTION TO THIS MATTER.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERGIRL MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENTS WILL COME
COLLECT THAT FROM YOU. >> PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
AND MADAM CLERK, WE'RE GOING TO SKIP OVER CLOSED SESSION ITEM
42 FOR NOW LET'S AND WE'LL DO CLOSED SESSION AT THE END OF
THE MEETING. LET'S GO TO OUR FOR ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 43 THROUGH 55 YES
ITEMS 43 THROUGH 55 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION
OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING.
ANY SUPERVISOR MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO
GO TO COMMITTEE SUPERVISOR MR. I JUST WANT TO BE ADDED AS A
CO-SPONSOR TO ITEM 51 PLEASE. OKAY, MADAM CLERK.
YOU GOT THAT? YES, NOTED.
THANK YOU. I WOULD LIKE TO SEVER 43 4748
AND 50 540 347 AND 55 MR. BOND 40 EIGHT AND 48.
>> THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
ON THE REMAINING BALANCE OF THE ITEMS, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
THE ROLL. >> THAT WOULD BE ITEMS 4244 42
OH THAT IS THE CLOSED SESSION. >> PARDON ME.
SOMETHING ABOUT THAT WOULD BE ITEMS 4440 FIVE, 46, 49, 5051,
5253 AND 54. SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON ALTERNATE I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
NEITHER ARE LEBANESE ALL RIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED AND MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 43 ITEM 43 THIS ITEM IS ON SECOND APPEARANCE AND HAS AN
EIGHT VOTE THRESHOLD. THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO URGE
THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT AND DEPARTMENT OF
TECHNOLOGY TO PRIORITIZE THE RESTORATION OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
OUTDOOR PUBLIC WARNING SYSTEM AND TSUNAMI EVACUATIONS ZONES
AND COASTAL AREAS AND TO ALLOCATE FUNDING FOR THIS
CRITICAL AND PUBLIC SAFETY INFRASTRUCTURE.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 43.
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN NO MANDEL MAN NO SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WANG WONG I
AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHAN EITHER ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO WITH
SUPERVISOR MANDEL MEN VOTING NO THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 47 ITEM 47 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
SUPPORT CALIFORNIA STATE SENATE BILL NUMBER 875 INTRODUCED BY
STATE SENATOR SCOTT WEINER WHICH WILL STRENGTHEN
AND PROTECT THE ABILITY OF LOCAL JURISDICTIONS WITHIN THE
PACIFIC GAS AND ELECTRIC SERVICE TERRITORY TO FORM OR
EXPAND THEIR OWN PUBLIC UTILITIES.
ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, TODAY WE'RE CONSIDERING THIS
RESOLUTION OF SUPPORT FOR SB 875 WHICH MAKES SEVERAL CHANGES
TO THE LEGAL PROCESS BY WHICH A PUBLIC UTILITY CAN ACQUIRE
ASSETS OF AN INVESTOR OWNED UTILITY THROUGH THE EXERCISE OF
EMINENT DOMAIN. SPECIFICALLY, THIS LEGISLATION
REMOVES SPECIAL PROTECTIONS THAT INVESTOR OWNED UTILITIES
CURRENTLY ENJOY AND THEIR ABILITY TO RECOVER LITIGATION
EXPENSES FROM MUNICIPALITIES ATTEMPTING TO ACQUIRE THE
ASSETS. IT ALSO LIMITS THE SCOPE OF THE
CALIFORNIA PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION'S REVIEW OF PUBLIC
UTILITY ASSET TRANSFER RIGHTS TO A DETERMINATION OF FAIRNESS
TO THE AFFECTED EMPLOYEES ONLY .
TOGETHER THESE PROVISIONS COULD MAKE IT EASIER FOR A CITY TO
PURSUE PUBLIC POWER. WE'RE ALL PAINFULLY AWARE OF
THE DISRUPTION CAUSED BY THE BLACKOUTS IN DECEMBER AND OF
JEANNIE'S WHOLLY UNSATISFACTORY RESPONSE.
BUT IT'S BEEN WELL OVER A DECADE THAT PGE HAS STRUGGLED
AND FAILED TO PROVIDE SAFE AND RELIABLE SERVICE TO ITS
CUSTOMERS. IT DOES NOT HAVE TO BE THIS WAY
ACROSS THE COUNTRY AND RIGHT HERE IN CALIFORNIA WE HAVE
EXAMPLES OF CITIES LIKE SACRAMENTO AND PALO ALTO THAT
DELIVER PUBLIC POWER MORE CHEAPLY AND RELIABLY THAN
INVESTOR OWNED UTILITY MONOPOLIES.
UNFORTUNATELY THOSE SAME INVESTOR OWNED UTILITIES HAVE
RIGGED THE GAME WRITING SPECIAL PROTECTIONS FOR THEMSELVES INTO
EMINENT DOMAIN LAW THAT NO OTHER PROPERTY OWNER ENJOYS.
THIS NOT ONLY MAKES IT HARDER FOR CITIES LIKE SAN FRANCISCO
TO EXPLORE OUR PUBLIC POWER OPTIONS BUT ALSO GRANTS TPG ANY
UNDUE LEVERAGE IN ANY NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE CITY
WHETHER ABOUT THE ULTIMATE DISPOSITION OF ASSETS OR IN THE
DAY TO DAY EFFORTS TO GET PGE TO DELIVER THE SERVICE THAT SAN
FRANCISCANS, SAN FRANCISCO AND OUR RESIDENTS REASONABLY
EXPECT? AND THAT'S LEVERAGE FOR WHICH
OUR RESIDENTS ARE QUITE LITERALLY PAYING THE PRICE.
SB 875 SIMPLY LEVELS THE PLAYING FIELD.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS DORSEY, MAHMOOD SADR, MELGAR,
WONG AND FIELDER FOR THEIR SUPPORT FOR RESOLUTION AND I
WANT TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE RON LBJ FOR HIS WORK
AND OF COURSE SENATOR WIENER FOR HIS CONTINUED ADVOCACY ON
BEHALF OF SAN FRANCISCO ON THIS ISSUE.
AND WITH THAT COLLEAGUES, I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT FOR THE RESOLUTION. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEM 47 SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY
DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL
I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EITHER ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION
THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 48 ITEM
48 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO SUPPORT CALIFORNIA STATE
ASSEMBLY BILL NUMBER 1897 INTRODUCED BY ASSEMBLY MEMBER
MATT HANEY WHICH CLARIFIES LEGAL STANDARDS GOVERNING
CONTINUED TREATMENT FOR OFFENDERS WITH SEVERE MENTAL
ILLNESS AND STRENGTHENS EVIDENCE BASED EVALUATION
REQUIREMENTS. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES, THIS RESOLUTION SUPPORTS ASSEMBLYMEMBER HANEY'S
ASSEMBLY BILL 1897 LEGISLATION THAT AIMS TO ENSURE THAT PEOPLE
WITH SEVERE MENTAL ILLNESS EXITING PRISON RECEIVE THE
TREATMENT THEY NEED TREATMENT WITH WHICH THEY ARE MUCH MORE
LIKELY TO RE-OFFEND. >> CURRENT STATE LAW PROVIDES
SEVERAL CRITERIA BY WHICH COURTS DETERMINE IF AN
INCARCERATED INDIVIDUAL WITH SEVERE MENTAL ILLNESS SHOULD
RECEIVE MENTAL HEALTH TREATMENT FOLLOWING THEIR RELEASE.
ONE OF THESE IS A DETERMINATION OF THE LIKELIHOOD THAT THE
INDIVIDUAL BY REASON OF THEIR DISORDER MAY CAUSE PHYSICAL
HARM TO OTHERS. UNFORTUNATELY, THE
DETERMINATION RELIES ON EVALUATIONS THAT ARE NON
STANDARDIZED AND HIGHLY SUBJECTIVE LEAVING MANY WITHOUT
TREATMENT AS THEY LEAVE CUSTODY TOO OFTEN THEY GO ON TO CYCLE
BETWEEN EMERGENCY ROOMS, JAIL AND THE STREETS AND I THINK ALL
OF US HAVE SEEN THIS THAT OUTCOME IS BAD FOR THE
INDIVIDUAL BUT IT'S ALSO BAD FOR THE BROADER PUBLIC.
AB 1897 AMENDS THE LAW TO MANDATE THAT WHEN INDIVIDUALS
WITH SEVERE MENTAL ILLNESS ARE RELEASED FROM PRISON, THE
DETERMINATION OF WHETHER THEY NEED MENTAL HEALTH CARE IS
BASED ON STRUCTURED CLINICAL ASSESSMENT INSTEAD OF
GUESSWORK. IN DOING SO THE HOPE IS WE
CONNECT INDIVIDUALS TO TREATMENT SOONER, IMPROVE THEIR
STABILITY AND REDUCE THE RISK OF HARM TO THEMSELVES AND TO
OTHERS. I WANT TO THANK ASSEMBLYMEMBER
MAHONY FOR THIS LEGISLATION AND FOR DEMONSTRATING THAT
COMMUNITY SAFETY AND HUMANE TREATMENT OF PEOPLE WITH MENTAL
IT MENTAL ILLNESS ARE MUTUALLY AFFIRMING PRIORITIES.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR SÖDER FOR HIS CO-SPONSORSHIP
AND AGAIN I WANT TO THANK RON WILL BE JOY IN MY OFFICE FOR
HIS WORK ON THE RESOLUTION WITH THAT COLLEAGUES I RESPECTFULLY
ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT AND I THINK WE CAN PROBABLY TAKE THIS
SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 55. >> ITEM 55.
THIS IS A MOTION TO AUTHORIZE PREPARATION OF WRITTEN
PROPONENT AND OPPONENT BALLOT ARGUMENTS AND REBUTTAL BALLOT
BALLOT ARGUMENTS FOR SUBMITTAL TO THE VOTERS FOR THE JUNE
SECOND, 2026 STATEWIDE DIRECT PRIMARY ELECTION.
>> ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK, YOU HAVE CIRCULATED THOSE
AMENDMENTS THAT WE THINK REFLECT WHAT DIFFERENT FOLKS
WANT TO DO IN TERMS OF SIGNING ON TO THESE MEASURES.
>> I BELIEVE THAT I AM SUPPOSED TO READ THIS AMENDMENT
STATEMENT. >> IS THAT CORRECT?
MADAM CLERK CERTAINLY, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. SO I'M GOING TO LOOK FOR A
MOTION TO AMEND TO AMEND THE MOTION TO DESIGNATE SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD TO WRITE THE PROPONENT ARGUMENT FOR THE CHARTER
AMENDMENT ON LIFETIME TERM LIMITS.
DESIGNATE MAYOR LURIE TO WRITE THE PROPONENT ARGUMENT FOR THE
G.O. BOND. DESIGNATE SUPERVISOR CHAN TO
WRITE THE OPPONENT ARGUMENT FOR THE CHARTER AMENDMENT ON
LIFETIME TERM LIMITS. STRIKE THE REMAINDER OF THE
OPPONENT ARGUMENT SECTION SINCE NO SUPERVISOR EXPRESSED
INTEREST IN THE OTHER THREE MEASURES AND MAKE OTHER
CLARIFYING AND CONFORMING CHANGES.
DID I GET THAT RIGHT MADAM CLERK THAT'S PERFECTLY ALL
RIGHT BUT I NEED SOMEONE TO MAKE THAT MOTION MADE BY
MAHMOOD AND I NEED A SECOND WHICH I THINK I JUST GOT FROM
CHERYL AND MADAM CLERK WE CAN TAKE THAT SAME HOUSE, MR.
PRESIDENT. >> I WILL TAKE THE AMENDMENTS.
>> TAKE THE AMENDMENTS FIRST. ALL RIGHT.
WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDMENTS WITHOUT OBJECTION.
ALL RIGHT. WITH WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE MOTION IS AMENDED. OKAY.
AND THEN ON THE AMENDED MOTION WE CAN TAKE THAT SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL, SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
MOTION IS ADOPTED. THE AMENDED MOTION IS ADOPTED.
>> OKAY. WELL, OKAY.
ALL RIGHT. THANKS EVERYBODY AND ESPECIALLY
MADAM CLERK. WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S
GO TO OUR CLOSED SESSION PLEASE CALL ITEM 42.
ITEM 42. THIS CONFERENCE WITH THE CITY
ATTORNEY HAS BEEN SCHEDULED PURSUANT TO A MOTION M26 DASH
ZERO 18 CONTAINED IN FILE NUMBER 260167 APPROVED ON
FEBRUARY 24TH 2026 IS THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS CONVENING THIS
CLOSED SESSION TODAY MARCH 3RD, 2026 FOR THE PURPOSE TO CONFER
WITH OR RECEIVE ADVICE FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY REGARDING THE
FOLLOWING EXISTING LITIGATION MATTER IN WHICH THE CITY IS A
PARTY AIRLINES FOR AMERICA VERSUS CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. UH I THINK NOW MEMBERS OF THE
PUBLIC WE'RE GOING TO ASK THAT YOU EXIT THE CHAMBER WHILE WE
GO INTO CLOSED SESSION. WE'RE GOING TO RESUME THE
MEETING AND OPEN SESSION AFTER WE CONCLUDE MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
LET US KNOW WHEN THE CHAMBER IS READY.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. WE WILL PREPARE THE CHAMBER.
ASAPH GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
AND S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
S.F. GOV TV SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNMENT TELEVISION
SHOW BREAK OUTLETS IN OKAY AND THAT'S ONE GAVEL OR DO WE
NEED TO WAKE THEM UP OKAY OKAY ALL RIGHT AND WE'RE READY OKAY
WHAT? >> ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, WE
ARE NOW BACK IN OPEN SESSION. NO ACTION WAS TAKEN IN CLOSED
SESSION MAY I HAVE A MOTION THAT THE BOARD FINDS THAT IS
IN THE BEST INTEREST THE PUBLIC THAT THE BOARD ELECT NOT TO
DISCLOSED ITS CLOSED SESSION DELIBERATIONS MOVED BY CHERYL
SECONDED BY WALTON MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
THE MOTION? >> NOT TO DISCLOSE SUPERVISOR
CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR
RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR DISORDER SORTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR ONE WONG I
AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION WE WILL NOT DISCLOSE OUR CLOSED SESSION
DELIBERATIONS AND SEEING NO OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER THIS
CLOSED SESSION HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED MADAM CLERK DO
WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT. MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU PLEASE
READ THE IN MEMORIAM? >> WE HAVE NONE TO REPORT, MR.
PRESIDENT. AND THAT BRINGS US TO THE END
OF OUR AGENDA. I BELIEVE, MADAM CLERK, DO WE
HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. WE ARE ADJOURNED